<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1252"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-pce-stateful-path-protection-11" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Stateful PCE LSP Path Protection">PCEP Extensions for Associating Working and Protection LSPs with Stateful PCE</title>
    <author fullname="Hariharan Ananthakrishnan" initials="H." surname="Ananthakrishnan">
      <organization>Netflix</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
            <street/>
          <city/>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>hari@netflix.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Siva Sivabalan" initials="S." surname="Sivabalan">
        <organization>Cisco</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>2000 Innovation Drive</street>
                <city>Kananta, Ontaria K2K 3E8</city>
                <country>Canada</country>
            </postal>
            <email>msiva@cisco.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Colby Barth" initials="C." surname="Barth">
        <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>1194 N Mathilda Ave,</street>
                <city>Sunnyvale, CA, 94086</city>
                <country>USA</country>
            </postal>
            <email>cbarth@juniper.net</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Ina Minei" initials="I." surname="Minei">
        <organization>Google, Inc</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
                <city>Mountain View, CA, 94043</city>
                <country>USA</country>
            </postal>
            <email>inaminei@google.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="M" surname="Negi" fullname="Mahendra Singh Negi">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560066</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mahend.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>   
    <!-- month and day will be generated automatically by XML2RFC;
be sure the year is current.-->

    <date year="2019"/> <!--02 as uploaded-->

    <workgroup>PCE Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>PCEP</keyword>

<abstract>
<t> An active stateful Path Computation Element (PCE) is capable of computing as well as controlling via 
Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) Multiprotocol Label Switching Traffic Engineering (MPLS-TE) Label Switched Paths (LSPs).  
Furthermore, it is also possible for an active stateful PCE to create, maintain, and delete LSPs. This document defines the PCEP extension to associate two or more LSPs to provide end-to-end path protection.</t>
</abstract>
 
</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t><xref target="RFC5440"/> describes Path Computation Element Communication Protocol for communication between a Path Computation Client (PCC) and a PCE or 
between a pair of PCEs as per <xref target="RFC4655"/>.  A PCE computes paths for MPLS-TE Label Switched Paths (LSPs) based on various constraints and optimization criteria. </t>

 <t>Stateful PCE <xref target="RFC8231"/> specifies a set of extensions to PCEP to enable 
stateful control of paths such as MPLS-TE LSPs between and across PCEP sessions in compliance with <xref target="RFC4657"/>. 
It includes mechanisms to effect LSP state synchronization between PCCs and PCEs,
delegation of control of LSPs to PCEs, and PCE control of timing and
sequence of path computations within and across PCEP sessions. The
focus is on a model where LSPs are configured on the PCC and control
over them is delegated to the Stateful PCE.

Furthermore, <xref target="RFC8281"/> specifies a mechanism to
dynamically instantiate LSPs on a PCC based on the requests from a
stateful PCE or a controller using stateful PCE.

</t>

<t>Path protection <xref target="RFC4427"/> refers to a paradigm in which the working LSP is protected by one or more protection LSP(s). 
When the working LSP fails, protection LSP(s) is/are activated. When the working LSPs are computed and controlled 
by the PCE, there is benefit in a mode of operation where protection LSPs are as well. <xref target="RFC8051"/> describes applicability of path protection in PCE deployments.</t>

<t>This document specifies a stateful PCEP extension to associate two or more LSPs for the purpose of setting up 
path protection. The extension defined in this document covers the following scenarios:
    <list style="symbols">
    <t>A PCC initiates a protection LSP and retains the control of the LSP. The PCC computes the path itself or makes a 
        request for path computation to a PCE. After the path setup, it reports the information and state of the path to the PCE. 
        This includes the association group identifying the working and protection LSPs.
        This is the passive stateful mode <xref target="RFC8051"/>.
    </t>
    <t>A PCC initiates a protection LSP and delegates the control of the LSP to a stateful PCE. During delegation the association group identifying the working and protection LSPs is included. The PCE 
    computes the path for the protection LSP and updates the PCC with the information about the path as long as it controls the LSP. 
    This is the active stateful mode <xref target="RFC8051"/>.
    </t>

    <t>A protection LSP could be initiated by a stateful PCE, which retains the control of the LSP. 
    The PCE is responsible for computing the path of the LSP and updating to the PCC with the information about the path. 
    This is the PCE-Initiated mode <xref target="RFC8281"/>.
    </t> 
    
    
      </list>


   Note that a protection LSP can be established (signaled) before
   the failure (in which case the LSP is said to be in standby mode
   <xref target="RFC4427"/> or a Primary LSP <xref target="RFC4872"/>) or after failure of the
   corresponding working LSP (known as a secondary LSP <xref target="RFC4872"/>).
   Whether to establish it before or after failure is according
   to operator choice or policy.

</t>
<t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> introduces a generic mechanism to
   create a grouping of LSPs, which can then be used to define
   associations between a set of LSPs.  The mechanism is equally
   applicable to stateful PCE (active and passive modes) and stateless
   PCE.</t>

   <t>This document specifies a PCEP extension to associate one working LSP with one or more
   protection LSPs using the generic association mechanism.</t>

   <t>This document describes a PCEP
   extension to associate protection LSPs by creating Path Protection Association Group (PPAG)
   and encoding this association in PCEP messages for stateful PCEP
   sessions.
   </t>
    <section title="Requirements Language" toc="default">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they
      appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
</section> <!-- Introduction --> 

<section title="Terminology">

<t>The following terminologies are used in this document:
      <list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="ERO:"> Explicit Route Object.</t>
        <t hangText="LSP:"> Label Switched Path.</t>
        <t hangText="PCC:"> Path Computation Client.</t>
        <t hangText="PCE:"> Path Computation Element</t>
        <t hangText="PCEP:"> Path Computation Element Communication Protocol.</t>
        <t hangText="PPAG:"> Path Protection Association Group.</t>
        <t hangText="TLV:"> Type, Length, and Value.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
</section> <!-- Terminology --> 
    
<section anchor="Extension-Overview" title="PCEP Extensions">

<section anchor="Path-Protection-Association-Type" title="Path Protection Association Type">

<t>As per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>, LSPs are not associated by listing the other LSPs with which they interact, but rather by making them 
belong to an association groups. All LSPs join an association group individually. The generic ASSOCIATION object is used to associate two 
or more LSPs as specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>. This document defines a new Association type called 
"Path Protection Association Type" of value TBD1 and a "Path Protection Association Group" (PPAG). 
A member LSP of a PPAG can 
take the role of working or protection LSP.  A PPAG can have one working LSP and/or one or more
protection LSPs. The source, destination and Tunnel ID (as carried in LSP-IDENTIFIERS TLV <xref target="RFC8231"/>, with description as per <xref target="RFC3209"/>) of all LSPs within a PPAG MUST be the same. As per <xref target="RFC3209"/>, TE tunnel is used to associate a set of LSPs during reroute or to spread a traffic trunk over multiple paths.</t>

<t>The format of the Association object used for PPAG is specified in 
<xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.</t>


<!--<figure anchor="PPAG-IPv4-Association-Object-Fmt" title="PPAG IPv4 ASSOCIATION Object format">
<artwork><![CDATA[

   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |         Reserved            |              Flags            |R|
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  Association type = TBD1    |          Association            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                IPv4 Association Source                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   //            Optional TLVs                                    //
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
       
<figure anchor="PPAG-IPv6-Association-Object-Fmt" title="PPAG IPv6 ASSOCIATION Object format">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |         Reserved            |              Flags            |R|
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  | Association type = TBD1     |          Association            |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                                                               |
  |                IPv6 Association Source                        |
  |                                                               |
  |                                                               |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  //            Optional TLVs                                    //
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
-->    

   <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> specifies the mechanism for the
   capability advertisement of the Association types supported by a PCEP
   speaker by defining a ASSOC-Type-List TLV to be carried within an
   OPEN object.  This capability exchange for the Association type
   described in this document (i.e.  Path Protection Association Type) MAY be
   done before using this association, i.e., the PCEP speaker MAY
   include the Path Protection Association Type (TBD1) in the ASSOC-Type-List TLV
   before using the PPAG in the PCEP messages.</t>
   <t>This Association type is dynamic in nature and created by the PCC or PCE for
   the LSPs belonging to the same TE tunnel (as described in <xref target="RFC3209"/>) originating at the same head node and terminating at the same destination.
   These associations are conveyed via PCEP messages to the PCEP peer. As per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>, 
   the association source is set to the local PCEP speaker address that created the association, 
   unless local policy dictates otherwise. Operator-configured Association Range MUST NOT be set for this Association type and MUST be ignored.</t>

</section> 

<section anchor="Path-Protection-Association-TLV" title="Path Protection Association TLV">
<t>The Path Protection Association TLV is an optional TLV for use in the ASSOCIATION Object
with the Path Protection Association Type. The Path Protection Association TLV MUST NOT be present more than once. 
If it appears more than once,
only the first occurrence is processed and any others MUST be ignored. </t>

<t> The Path Protection Association TLV follows the PCEP TLV format of <xref target="RFC5440"/>. </t> 

<t> The type (16 bits) of the TLV is TBD2. The length 
field (16 bit) has a fixed value of 4.</t> 
<t>The value comprises of a single field, the Path Protection Association
   Flags (32 bits), where each bit represents a flag option.</t>
<!--<t>The value comprises of two fields, the Protection Scheme (PS) (6 bits) and the Path Protection Association Flags (26 bits) (where each bit represents a
flag option). </t>-->

<t> The format of the <xref target="PPAG-TLV-Fmt"> Path Protection Association TLV</xref> is as follows:</t>

<figure anchor="PPAG-TLV-Fmt" title="Path Protection Association TLV format">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |         Type = TBD2         |              Length = 4         |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |   PT      |               Unassigned Flags                |S|P|
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

<t>Path Protection Association Flags (32 bits) -  The following flags are currently defined - 
    <list>
    <t>Protecting (P): 1 bit - This bit is as defined in Section 14.1 of <xref target="RFC4872"/> to indicate if the LSP is a working (0) or protection (1) LSP.</t>
    <t>Secondary (S): 1 bit - This bit is as defined in Section 14.1 of <xref target="RFC4872"/> to indicate if the LSP is a primary (0) or secondary (1) LSP. The S flag is ignored if the P flag is not set.</t>
    <t>Protection Type (PT): 6 bits - This field is as defined in Section 14.1 of <xref target="RFC4872"/> to indicate the LSP protection type in use. Any type already defined or
   that could be defined in the future for use in the RSVP-TE PROTECTION object is acceptable in this TLV unless explicitly stated otherwise.</t>
    <t>Unassigned bits are considered reserved.  They MUST be set to 0 on
   transmission and MUST be ignored on receipt. </t>
 </list></t>

<t>If the TLV is missing in PPAG, it is considered that the LSP is a working LSP (i.e. as if the P bit is unset).</t>
</section> <!-- PPAG TLV -->
</section> <!-- PCEP extensions --> 

<section anchor="Operation" title="Operation">
    <t>An LSP is associated with
   other LSPs with which it interacts by adding them to a common
   association group via the ASSOCIATION object. All procedures and error-handling for the ASSOCIATION 
   object is as per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.</t>

<section anchor="Operation-State-Sync" title="State Synchronization"> 

  <t>During state synchronization, a PCC reports all the existing LSP states as described in <xref target="RFC8231"/>.
   The association group membership pertaining to an LSP is also reported as per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>. This
   includes PPAGs.</t>

    </section> <!-- State Synchronization --> 


    <section anchor="Operation-PCC-Init" title="PCC-Initiated LSPs"> 

  <t>A PCC can associate a set of LSPs under its control for path protection purposes. Similarly, the PCC can 
  remove one or more LSPs under its control from the corresponding PPAG. In both cases, the PCC reports 
  the change in association to PCE(s) via Path Computation Report (PCRpt) messages. A PCC can also delegate the working and protection 
  LSPs to an active stateful PCE, where the PCE would control the LSPs. The stateful PCE could update the paths and attributes of the LSPs in the association group 
  via Path Computation Update (PCUpd) message. A PCE could also update the association to the PCC via PCUpd message. These procedures are described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.
</t>
<t>It is expected that both working and protection LSPs are delegated together (and to the same PCE) to avoid any race conditions. Refer to <xref target="I-D.litkowski-pce-state-sync"/> for the problem description.</t>

</section> <!-- PCC-Initiated LSPs --> 

    <section anchor="Operation-PCE-Init" title="PCE-Initiated LSPs"> 

    <t>A PCE can create/update working and protection LSPs independently. 
    As specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>, 
    Association Groups can be created by both the PCE and the PCC. 
    Further, a PCE can remove a protection LSP from a PPAG as specified in 
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>. The PCE uses PCUpd 
    or Path Computation Initiate (PCInitiate) messages to communicate the association information to the PCC.</t>

    </section> <!-- PCE-Initiated LSPs --> 




    <section anchor="Session-Termination" title="Session Termination"> 

  <t>As per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> the association information is cleared along with the LSP state
   information.  When a PCEP
   session is terminated, after expiry of State Timeout Interval at the PCC,
   the LSP state associated with that PCEP session is reverted to
   operator-defined default parameters or behaviors as per <xref target="RFC8231"/>. The same procedure is
   also followed for the association information.  On session
   termination at the PCE, when the LSP state reported by PCC is
   cleared, the association information is also cleared as per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.  Where there
   are no LSPs in a association group, the association is considered to
   be deleted.</t>

    </section> <!-- State Synchronization --> 

<section anchor="Operation-Error-Handling" title="Error Handling"> 
  <t>As per the processing rules specified in section 6.4 of
   <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>, if a PCEP speaker does not support
   this Path Protection Association Type, it would return a PCErr message with
   Error-Type 26 "Association Error" and Error-Value 1 "Association type is not supported".</t> 
  <t>All LSPs (working or protection) within a PPAG MUST belong to the same TE Tunnel (as described in <xref target="RFC3209"/>) and have the same source and destination. 
  If a PCEP speaker attempts to add or update an LSP to a PPAG and the Tunnel ID (as carried in LSP-IDENTIFIERS TLV <xref target="RFC8231"/>, with description as per <xref target="RFC3209"/>) or source or destination of the LSP is different from 
  the LSP(s) in the PPAG, the PCEP speaker MUST send PCErr with Error-Type 26 (Association Error) <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>
  and Error-Value TBD3 (Tunnel ID or End points mismatch for Path Protection Association). In case of Path Protection, LSP-IDENTIFIERS TLV SHOULD be included for all LSPs (including Segment Routing (SR) <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/>). If the Protection Type (PT) (in Path Protection Association TLV) is different from the LSPs in the PPAG, the PCEP speaker MUST send PCErr with Error-Type 26 (Association Error) <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>
  and Error-Value 6 (Association information mismatch) as per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.</t>

  <t>When the PCEP peer does not support the protection type set in PPAG, the PCEP peer MUST send PCErr with Error-Type 26 (Association Error) 
  <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> and Error-Value TBD5 (Protection type is not supported).</t>

  <t>A given LSP MAY belong to more than one PPAG. If there is a conflict between any of the two PPAGs, the PCEP peer MUST send PCErr with Error-Type 26 (Association Error) <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> and Error-Value 6 (Association information mismatch) as per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.</t>
  
  <t>When the protection type is set to 1+1, there MUST be at maximum, only one working LSP and one protection LSP within a PPAG.
  If a PCEP speaker attempts to add another working/protection LSP,
  the PCEP peer MUST send PCErr with Error-Type 26 (Association Error) <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> 
  and Error-Value TBD4 (Attempt to add another working/protection LSP for Path Protection Association).</t> 

  <t>When the protection type is set to 1:N, there MUST be at maximum, only one working LSP and number of protection LSPs MUST NOT be more than N within a PPAG. If a PCEP speaker attempts to add another working/protection LSP,
  the PCEP peer MUST send PCErr with Error-Type 26 (Association Error) <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> 
  and Error-Value TBD4 (Attempt to add another working/protection LSP for Path Protection Association).</t>


    
  <!--<t>When the protection type is set to 1:N with N>1:
  <list>
  <t>If there is only one PPAG, there MUST be only one working LSP and number of protection LSPs MUST NOT be more than N within a PPAG.</t>
  <t>If there are multiple PPAGs, in each PPAG there must be only one working LSP and total number of protection LSPs in all the PPAGs MUST NOT be more than N.</t>
  <t>If above conditions are not satisfied, the PCEP peer MUST send PCErr with Error-Type 26 (Early allocation by IANA) (Association Error) 
    <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref> and Error-Value 6 (Association information mismatch).</t>

  <t>If PCEP peer does not support 1:N protection, the PCEP peer MUST send PCErr with Error-Type 26 (Early allocation by IANA) (Association Error) 
    <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref> and Error-Value TBD5 (Protection type is not supported).</t>
  </list>
  </t>-->
  <t>All processing as per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> continues to apply.</t>
  </section> <!-- Error Handling --> 

</section> <!-- Operation --> 
<section title="Other Considerations">
    <t>The working and protection LSPs are
   typically resource disjoint (e.g., node, SRLG disjoint).  This
   ensures that a single failure will not affect both the working and
   protection LSPs. The disjoint requirement for a group of LSPs is handled via another Association type called
        "Disjointness Association", as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-diversity"/>. 
        The diversity requirements for the protection LSP are also handled by including both ASSOCIATION
        objects identifying both the protection association group and the disjoint association group for the group of LSPs.</t>
        <t><xref target="RFC4872"/> introduces the concept and mechanisms to support the
   association of one LSP to another LSP across different RSVP Traffic Engineering (RSVP-TE) sessions using ASSOCIATION and PROTECTION object.
   The information in the Path Protection Association TLV in PCEP as received from the PCE is used
   to trigger the signaling of working LSP and protection LSP, with the Path
   Protection Association Flags mapped to the corresponding fields in the
   PROTECTION Object in RSVP-TE.</t>

</section>    
<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>[Note to RFC Editor and IANA: Sections 3.1, 3.2, and 4.5 contain "TBD1" through
"TBD5" those should be replaced by the values that IANA assigns.]</t>
    <section title="Association Type">

    <t>This document defines a new Association type, originally
    defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>, for path protection. 
    IANA is requested to make the assignment of a new value for the
    sub-registry "ASSOCIATION Type Field" (request to be created in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>), as follows: </t>
            <texttable>
            <ttcol>Association type Value</ttcol><ttcol>Association Name    </ttcol><ttcol>Reference</ttcol>
            <c> TBD1 </c><c> Path Protection Association</c> <c> This     document </c>
            </texttable>
    
    </section>
    
    <section title="Path Protection Association TLV">

      <t> This document defines a new TLV for carrying additional information of LSPs within a path protection association group.
      IANA is requested to make the assignment of a new value for the
   existing "PCEP TLV Type Indicators" registry as follows:</t>

        <texttable>
        <ttcol>TLV Type Value</ttcol><ttcol>TLV Name</ttcol><ttcol> Reference</ttcol>
        <c> TBD2 </c><c>Path Protection Association Group TLV</c> <c> This document </c>
        </texttable>

<t> This document requests that a new sub-registry, named "Path protection Association Group TLV Flag Field", 
is created within the "Path Computation
   Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers" registry to manage the Flag field in
   the Path Protection Association Group TLV.
   New values are to be assigned by Standards Action <xref target="RFC8126"/>.  Each
   bit should be tracked with the following qualities:
<list style="symbols">
    <t>Bit number (count from 0 as the most significant bit) </t>
    <t>Name flag </t> 
    <t>Reference </t> 
</list>
</t>
   
<texttable anchor="PPAG-TLV-Table-IANA" title="Path Protection Association TLV Flag Field">
    <ttcol align="center">Bit Number</ttcol>
    <ttcol align="center">Name</ttcol>
    <ttcol align="center">Reference</ttcol>
    <c>31</c>
    <c>P - PROTECTION-LSP</c>
    <c>This document </c>
    <c>30</c>
    <c>S - SECONDARY-LSP</c>
    <c>This document</c>
    <c>0-5</c>
    <c>Protection Type Flags</c>
    <c>This document </c>
</texttable>

    </section>

      <section title="PCEP Errors">

    <t>This document defines new Error-Values related to  path protection association for Error-type 26 "Association Error" defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>. 
        IANA is requested to allocate new error values within the "PCEP-ERROR
   Object Error Types and Values" sub-registry of the PCEP Numbers
   registry, as follows:</t>
          <t>Error-type: 26 "Association Error" <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/></t> 
          <texttable>
           <ttcol> Error-value </ttcol><ttcol> Meaning </ttcol><ttcol> Reference </ttcol>
           <c> TBD3 </c> <c>Tunnel ID or End points mismatch for Path Protection Association</c> <c> This document</c>
           
           <c> TBD4 </c> <c>Attempt to add another working/protection LSP for Path Protection Association</c> <c> This document</c>

           <c> TBD5 </c> <c>Protection type is not supported</c> <c> This document</c>
           
          </texttable>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
        <t>
               The security considerations described in <xref target="RFC8231"/>, 
               <xref target="RFC8281"/>, and <xref target="RFC5440"/> 
               apply to the extensions described in this document as
   well.  Additional considerations related to associations where 
   a malicious PCEP speaker could be spoofed and could be used as
   an attack vector by creating associations as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.
   Adding a spurious protection LSP to the Path Protection Association group could give false sense of network reliability, which leads to issues when the working LSP is down and the protection LSP fails as well. Thus securing the PCEP session using
   Transport Layer Security (TLS) <xref target="RFC8253"/>, as per the
   recommendations and best current practices in BCP 195 <xref target="RFC7525"/>, is
   RECOMMENDED.
        </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Manageability Considerations" toc="default">
      <section title="Control of Function and Policy" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any control or policy 
            requirements in addition to those already listed in
        <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and 
        <xref target="RFC8281"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Information and Data Models" toc="default">
        <t><xref target="RFC7420"/> describes the PCEP MIB, there are no new MIB Objects
        for this document.</t>
        <t>The PCEP YANG module <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang"/> supports
        associations.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Liveness Detection and Monitoring" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new liveness detection
        and monitoring requirements in addition to those already listed in
        <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and 
        <xref target="RFC8281"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Verify Correct Operations" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new operation
        verification requirements in addition to those already listed in
        <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and 
        <xref target="RFC8281"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Requirements On Other Protocols" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new requirements
        on other protocols.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Impact On Network Operations" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not have any impact on
        network operations in addition to those already listed in
        <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and 
        <xref target="RFC8281"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgments">
    <t>We would like to thank Jeff Tantsura, Xian Zhang and Greg Mirsky for their contributions to this document.</t>
    <t>Thanks to Ines Robles for the RTGDIR review.</t>
    <t>Thanks to Pete Resnick for the GENART review.</t>
    <t>Thanks to Donald Eastlake for the SECDIR review.</t>
    <t>Thanks to Barry Leiba for the IESG review.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
    
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3209"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4872"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5440"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7525"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8231"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8253"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8281"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"?>        
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4427"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4655"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4657"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7420"?>
        
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8051"?>
        
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pce-association-diversity"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.litkowski-pce-state-sync"?>
    </references>
<section title="Contributor Addresses" toc="default">
    <t>
    <figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
          <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[
Dhruv Dhody
Huawei Technologies
Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield
Bangalore, Karnataka  560066
India

EMail: dhruv.ietf@gmail.com
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
  </t>
  
  <t>
    <figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
          <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[
Raveendra Torvi
Juniper Networks
1194 N Mathilda Ave,
Sunnyvale, CA, 94086
USA

EMail: rtorvi@juniper.net

        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
  </t>

  <t>
    <figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
          <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[
Edward Crabbe
Individual Contributor

EMail: edward.crabbe@gmail.com
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
  </t>
</section>   
</back>
</rfc>