<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="Yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-pce-binding-label-sid-13"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Binding Label/SID">Carrying Binding Label/Segment
    Identifier (SID) in PCE-based Networks.</title>

    <author fullname="Siva Sivabalan" initials="S." surname="Sivabalan">
      <organization>Ciena Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>msiva282@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Clarence Filsfils" initials="C." surname="Filsfils">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Pegasus Parc</street>

          <city>De kleetlaan 6a</city>

          <region>DIEGEM</region>

          <code>BRABANT 1831</code>

          <country>BELGIUM</country>
        </postal>

        <email>cfilsfil@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jeff Tantsura" initials="J." surname="Tantsura">
      <organization>Microsoft Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>jefftant.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <!--<author fullname="Jonathan Hardwick" initials="J." surname="Hardwick">
      <organization>Metaswitch Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>100 Church Street</street>

          <city>Enfield</city>

          <region>Middlesex</region>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>Jonathan.Hardwick@metaswitch.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>-->

    <author fullname="Stefano Previdi" initials="S." surname="Previdi">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>stefano@previdi.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <!--<author fullname="Dhruv Dhody" initials="D."  surname="Dhody">
   <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka 560066</region>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>dhruv.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>-->

    <author fullname="Cheng Li (editor)" initials="C." surname="Li, Ed.">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>c.l@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="2" month="February" year="2022"/>

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>PCE Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>In order to provide greater scalability, network confidentiality, and
      service independence, Segment Routing (SR) utilizes a Binding Segment
      Identifier (SID) (called BSID) as described in RFC 8402. It is possible to associate a BSID to an
      RSVP-TE-signaled Traffic Engineering Label Switched Path or an SR
      Traffic Engineering path. The BSID can be used by an upstream node for
      steering traffic into the appropriate TE path to enforce SR policies.
      This document specifies the concept of binding value, which can be either an MPLS label or Segment
      Identifier. It further specifies an extension to Path Computation Element (PCE) communication
      Protocol(PCEP) for reporting the binding value by a Path Computation Client (PCC) to the PCE to support PCE-based Traffic Engineering
      policies. </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>A Path Computation Element (PCE) can compute Traffic Engineering
      paths (TE paths) through a network where those paths are subject to
      various constraints. Currently, TE paths are set up using either the
      RSVP-TE signaling protocol or Segment Routing (SR). We refer to such
      paths as RSVP-TE paths and SR-TE paths respectively in this
      document.</t>

      <t>As per <xref target="RFC8402"/> SR allows a head-end node to steer a
      packet flow along a given path via a Segment Routing Policy (SR Policy). As per <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing-policy"/>, an SR Policy is a
      framework that enables the instantiation of an ordered list of segments
      on a node for implementing a source routing policy with a specific
      intent for traffic steering from that node.</t>

      <t>As described in <xref target="RFC8402"/>, a Binding Segment
      Identifier (BSID) is bound to a Segment Routing (SR) Policy,
      instantiation of which may involve a list of Segment Identifiers (SIDs).
      Any packets received with an active segment equal to a BSID are steered
      onto the bound SR Policy. A BSID may be either a local (SR Local Block
      (SRLB)) or a global (SR Global Block (SRGB)) SID. As per Section 6.4 of
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing-policy"/> a BSID can also
      be associated with any type of interface or tunnel to enable the use of
      a non-SR interface or tunnel as a segment in a SID list. In this
      document, the term 'binding label/SID' is used to generalize the allocation of
      binding value for both SR and non-SR paths.</t>

      <!--<t>Similar to assigning label to a Forwarding Equivalence Class (FEC) via Label Distribution Protocol (LDP), a binding label can be assigned to a RSVP-TE LSP. If the topmost label of an incoming packet is the binding label, the packet is steered onto the RSVP-TE LSP.
  As such, any upstream node can use binding labels to steer the packets that it originates to appropriate TE LSPs to enforce TE/SR policy. Similarly, a binding SID, see <xref target="I-D.ietf-isis-segment-routing-extensions"/>, <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-segment-routing-te-policy"/>
and <xref target="RFC8402"/> can be used to enforce SR policy with SR-TE path. Note that if an SR-TE path is represented as a forwarding-adjacency (FA), then the corresponding adjacency SID can be used as the binding SID. In such case, the path is advertised using the routing protocols as described in <xref target="RFC4206"/>. The binding SID provides an alternate mechanism without additional overhead on routing protocols.</t>-->

      <t><xref target="RFC5440"/> describes the PCEP for communication between a Path Computation Client (PCC)
      and a PCE or between a pair of PCEs as per <xref target="RFC4655"/>.
      <xref target="RFC8231"/> specifies extensions to PCEP that allow a PCC
      to delegate its Label Switched Paths (LSPs) to a stateful PCE. A
      stateful PCE can then update the state of LSPs delegated to it. <xref
      target="RFC8281"/> specifies a mechanism allowing a PCE to dynamically
      instantiate an LSP on a PCC by sending the path and characteristics. 
      This document specifies an extension to PCEP to manage the binding of label/SID for both SR and non-SR paths.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC8664"/> provides a mechanism for a PCE (acting as a
      network controller) to instantiate SR-TE paths (candidate paths) for an
      SR Policy onto a head-end node (acting as a PCC) using PCEP. For more
      information on the SR Policy Architecture, see <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing-policy"/>.</t>

<section anchor="Motivation" title="Motivation and Example">

      <t>A binding label/SID has local significance to the ingress node of the
      corresponding TE path. When a stateful PCE is deployed for setting up TE
      paths, a binding label/SID reported from the PCC to
      the stateful PCE is useful for the purpose of enforcing end-to-end TE/SR policy. A
      sample Data Center (DC) and IP/MPLS WAN use-case is illustrated in <xref
      target="figure1"/> with a multi-domain PCE. In the IP/MPLS WAN, an SR-TE LSP is set up
      using the PCE. The list of SIDs of the SR-TE LSP is {A, B, C, D}. The
      gateway node 1 (which is the PCC) allocates a binding SID X and reports
      it to the PCE. In the MPLS DC network, an end-to-end SR-TE LSP is established. In order for the access node to steer the traffic towards Node-1 and over
      the SR-TE path in WAN, the PCE passes the SID stack {Y, X} where Y is the node
      SID of the gateway node-1 to the access node and X is the BSID. In the absence of the
      BSID X, the PCE would need to pass the SID stack {Y, A, B, C, D} to the
      access node. This example also illustrates the additional benefit of
      using the binding label/SID to reduce the number of SIDs imposed by the
      access nodes with a limited forwarding capacity.</t>

      <figure anchor="figure1" title="A Sample Use-case of Binding SID">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

           SID stack
           {Y, X}              +--------------+
                               | Multi-domain |
    _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _|     PCE      |
   |                           +--------------+
   |                              ^
   |                              | Binding
   |           .-----.            | SID (X)     .-----.
   |          (       )           |            (       )
   V       .--(         )--.      |        .--(         )--.
+------+  (                 )  +-------+  (                 )  +-------+
|Access|_(  MPLS DC Network  )_|Gateway|_(    IP/MPLS WAN    )_|Gateway|
| Node | (  ==============>  ) |Node-1 | ( ================> ) |Node-2 |
+------+  (    SR-TE path   )  +-------+  (    SR-TE path   )  +-------+
           '--(         )--'    Node       '--(         )--'
               (       )        SID of         (       )
                '-----'         Node-1          '-----'
                                is Y            SIDs for SR-TE LSP:
                                                {A, B, C, D}


]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Using the extension defined in this document, a PCC could report to the stateful PCE the binding label/SID it
      allocated via a Path Computation LSP State Report (PCRpt) message. It is
      also possible for a stateful PCE to request a PCC to allocate a specific
      binding label/SID by sending a Path Computation LSP Update Request
      (PCUpd) message. If the PCC can successfully allocate the specified
      binding value, it reports the binding value to the PCE. Otherwise, the
      PCC sends an error message to the PCE indicating the cause of the
      failure. A local policy or configuration at the PCC SHOULD dictate if
      the binding label/SID needs to be assigned.</t>
</section>
<section anchor="Summary" title="Summary of the Extension">
      <t>To implement the needed changes to PCEP, in this document, we introduce a new OPTIONAL TLV that a PCC can use
      in order to report the binding label/SID associated with a TE LSP, or a
      PCE to request a PCC to allocate any or a specific binding label/SID value.
      This TLV is intended for TE LSPs established using RSVP-TE, SR-TE, or any
      other future method. In the case of SR-TE LSPs, the TLV can carry
      a binding label (for SR-TE path with MPLS data-plane) or a binding IPv6
      SID (e.g., IPv6 address for SR-TE paths with IPv6 data-plane).
      Throughout this document, the term "binding value" means either an MPLS
      label or a SID.</t>

      <t>As another way to use the extension specified in this document, to support the PCE-based central controller <xref
      target="RFC8283"/> operation where the PCE would take responsibility for
      managing some part of the MPLS label space for each of the routers that
      it controls, the PCE could directly make the binding label/SID
      allocation and inform the PCC. See <xref target="PCECC"/> for
      details.</t>

      <t>In addition to specifying a new TLV, this document specifies how and when a PCC and PCE can use this TLV, how they can can allocate a binding label/SID, and associated error handling.</t>
    </section>
    </section>

    <!-- Introduction -->

    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when,
      they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The following terminologies are used in this document: <list
          style="hanging">
          <t hangText="BSID:">Binding Segment Identifier.</t>
          <t hangText="binding label/SID:">a generic term used for the binding segment for both SR and non-SR paths.</t>
          <t hangText="binding value:">a generic term used for the binding segment as it can be encoded in various formats (as per the binding type(BT)).</t>

          <!--<t hangText="LER:">Label Edge Router.</t>-->

          <t hangText="LSP:">Label Switched Path.</t>

          <!--<t hangText="LSR:">Label Switching Router.</t>-->

          <t hangText="PCC:">Path Computation Client.</t>

          <t hangText="PCEP:">Path Computation Element communication
          Protocol.</t>

          <t hangText="RSVP-TE:">Resource ReserVation Protocol-Traffic
          Engineering.</t>

          <t hangText="SID:">Segment Identifier.</t>

          <t hangText="SR:">Segment Routing.</t>

          <!--<t hangText="SRGB:">Segment Routing Global Block.</t>-->

          <!--<t hangText="SRLB:">Segment Routing Local Block.</t>-->
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <!-- Terminology -->

    <section anchor="TE-PATH-BINDING-TLV" title="Path Binding TLV">
      <t>The new optional TLV called "TE-PATH-BINDING TLV" (whose format is
      shown in <xref target="BINDING-LABEL-TLV-FORMAT"/>) is defined to carry
      the binding label/SID for a TE path. This TLV is associated with the LSP
      object specified in <xref target="RFC8231"/>. This TLV can also be
      carried in the PCEP-ERROR object <xref target="RFC5440"/> in case of
      error. Multiple instances of TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs MAY be present in the
      LSP and PCEP-ERROR object. The type of this TLV is 55 (early allocated
      by IANA). The length is variable.</t>

      <t>[Note to RFC Editor: Please remove "(early allocated by IANA)" before
      publication]</t>

      <figure anchor="BINDING-LABEL-TLV-FORMAT" title="TE-PATH-BINDING TLV">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |           Type = 55           |             Length            |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |      BT       |    Flags      |            Reserved           |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  ~            Binding Value (variable length)                    ~
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>TE-PATH-BINDING TLV is a generic TLV such that it is able to carry
      binding label/SID (i.e. MPLS label or SRv6 SID). It is formatted
      according to the rules specified in <xref target="RFC5440"/>. The value
      portion of the TLV comprises:</t>

      <t>Binding Type (BT): A one-octet field that identifies the type of
      binding included in the TLV. This document specifies the following BT
      values: <list style="symbols">
          <t>BT = 0: The binding value is a 20-bit MPLS label value. The TLV
          is padded to 4-bytes alignment. The Length MUST be set to 7 (the
          padding is not included in the length, as per <xref
          target="RFC5440"/> Section 7.1) and the first 20 bits are used to
          encode the MPLS label value.</t>

          <t>BT = 1: The binding value is a 32-bit MPLS label stack entry as
          per <xref target="RFC3032"/> with Label, TC <xref
          target="RFC5462"/>, S, and TTL values encoded. Note that the
          receiver MAY choose to override TC, S, and TTL values according to
          its local policy. The Length MUST be set to 8.</t>

          <t>BT = 2: The binding value is an SRv6 SID with the format of a
          16-octet IPv6 address, representing the binding SID for SRv6. The
          Length MUST be set to 20.</t>

          <t>BT = 3: The binding value is a 24 octet field, defined in <xref
          target="Behavior-Structure"/>, that contains the SRv6 SID as well as
          its Behavior and Structure. The Length MUST be set to 28.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t><xref target="IANA-TLV"/> defines the IANA registry used to maintain
      all these binding types as well as any future ones. Note that multiple
      TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs with same or different Binding Types MAY be present for the
      same LSP. A PCEP speaker could allocate multiple TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs (of the same BT), 
      and use different binding values in different domains or use-cases based on a local policy.</t>

      <t>Flags: 1 octet of flags. The following flag is defined in the new
      registry "TE-PATH-BINDING TLV Flag field" as described in <xref
      target="IANA-TLV"/>:</t>

      <figure anchor="BINDING-LABEL-FLAGS" suppress-title="false"
              title="Flags">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |R|             |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

      ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>where: <list style="symbols">
          <t>R (Removal - 1 bit): When set, the requesting PCEP peer requires
          the removal of the binding value for the LSP. When unset, the PCEP
          peer indicates that the binding value is added or retained for the
          LSP. This flag is used in the PCRpt and PCUpd messages. It is
          ignored in other PCEP messages.</t>

          <t>The unassigned flags MUST be set to 0 while sending and ignored
          on receipt.</t>
        </list></t>

      <!--Currently no flags are defined. </t>-->

      <!--Following flags are defined in the new
      registry "TE-PATH-BINDING TLV Flag field" as described in <xref
      target="IANA-TLV"/>:</t>

      <figure anchor="BINDING-LABEL-FLAGS" suppress-title="false" title="Flags">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |           |I|S|
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

      ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>where: <list style="symbols">
          <t>S-Flag: This flag encodes the "Specified-BSID-only" behavior. It
          is used as described in Section 6.2.3 of <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing-policy"/>.</t>

          <t>I-Flag: This flag encodes the "Drop Upon Invalid" behavior. It is
          used as described in Section 8.2 of <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing-policy"/>.</t>

          <t>Unassigned bits MUST be set to 0 while sending and ignored on
          receipt.</t>
        </list></t>-->

      <t>Reserved: MUST be set to 0 while sending and ignored on receipt.</t>

      <t>Binding Value: A variable-length field, padded with trailing zeros to
      a 4-octet boundary. When the BT is 0, the 20 bits represent the MPLS
      label. When the BT is 1, the 32 bits represent the MPLS label stack
      entry as per <xref target="RFC3032"/>. When the BT is 2, the 128 bits
      represent the SRv6 SID. When the BT is 3, the Binding Value also
      contains the SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure, defined in <xref
      target="Behavior-Structure"/>. In this document, the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV is considered to be empty if no Binding Value is present. Note that the length of the TLV would be 4 in such a case.</t>

      <section anchor="Behavior-Structure"
               title="SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure">
        <t>This section specifies the format of the Binding Value in the
        TE-PATH-BINDING TLV when the BT is set to 3 for the SRv6 Binding SIDs
        <xref target="RFC8986"/>. The format is shown in <xref
        target="SID-BEHAVIOR-AND-STRUCTURE"/>.</t>

        <figure anchor="SID-BEHAVIOR-AND-STRUCTURE"
                title="SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                                                               |
  |                 SRv6 Binding SID (16 octets)                  |
  |                                                               |
  |                                                               | 
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |         Reserved              |      Endpoint Behavior        |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |    LB Length  |    LN Length  | Fun. Length   |  Arg. Length  |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The Binding Value consists of:<list style="symbols">
            <t>SRv6 Binding SID: 16 octets. The 128-bit IPv6 address,
            representing the binding SID for SRv6.</t>

            <t>Reserved: 2 octets. It MUST be set to 0 on transmit and ignored
            on receipt.</t>

            <t>Endpoint Behavior: 2 octets. The Endpoint Behavior code point
            for this SRv6 SID as per the IANA subregistry called "SRv6
            Endpoint Behaviors", created by <xref target="RFC8986"/>. When the
            field is set with the value 0, the endpoint behavior is considered
            unknown.</t>

            <t>The following fields are used to advertise the length of each
            individual part of the SRv6 SID as defined in <xref
            target="RFC8986"/>:<list style="symbols">
                <t>LB Length: 1 octet. SRv6 SID Locator Block length in
                bits.</t>

                <t>LN Length: 1 octet. SRv6 SID Locator Node length in
                bits.</t>

                <t>Function Length: 1 octet. SRv6 SID Function length in
                bits.</t>

                <t>Argument Length: 1 octet. SRv6 SID Arguments length in
                bits.</t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>
          <t>The total of the locator block, locator node, function, and argument
lengths MUST be lower or equal to 128 bits.  If this condition is not
met, the corresponding TE-PATH-BINDING TLV MUST be considered 
as an error. Also, if the Endpoint Behavior is found to be unknown or
inconsistent, it is considered an error.  A PCErr message with 
Error-Type = 10 ("Reception of an invalid object") and Error-Value = 
37 ("Invalid SRv6 SID Structure") MUST be sent.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- Path-setup-type-tlv -->

    <section anchor="Operation" title="Operation">
      <t>The binding value is usually allocated by the PCC and reported to a PCE via a
      PCRpt message (see <xref target="PCECC"/> where PCE does the allocation). If a PCE does not recognize the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV, it
      would ignore the TLV in accordance with <xref target="RFC5440"/>. If a
      PCE recognizes the TLV but does not support the TLV, it MUST send a
      PCErr with Error-Type = 2 (Capability not supported).</t>

      <t>Multiple TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs are allowed to be present in the same
      LSP object. This signifies the presence of multiple binding SIDs for the
      given LSP. In the case of multiple TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs, the existing
      instances of TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs MAY be included in the LSP object. In
      case of an error condition, the whole message is rejected and the
      resulting PCErr message MAY include the offending TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in
      the PCEP-ERROR object.</t>

      <t>If a PCE recognizes an invalid binding value (e.g., label value from
      the reserved MPLS label space), it MUST send a PCErr message with
      Error-Type = 10 ("Reception of an invalid object") and Error Value = 2
      ("Bad label value") as specified in <xref target="RFC8664"/>.</t>

      <t>For SRv6 BSIDs, it is RECOMMENDED to always explicitly specify the
      SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure in the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV by
      setting the BT (Binding Type) to 3. This enables the sender to have
      control of the SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure. A sender MAY
      choose to set the BT to 2, in which case the receiving implementation
      chooses how to interpret the SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure
      according to local policy.</t>

      <t>If a PCC wishes to withdraw a previously reported binding value, it
      MUST send a PCRpt message with the specific TE-PATH-BINDING TLV with R
      flag set to 1. If a PCC wishes to modify a previously reported binding,
      it MUST withdraw the former binding value (with R flag set in the former
      TE-PATH-BINDING TLV) and include a new TE-PATH-BINDING TLV containing
      the new binding value. Note that other instances of TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs
      that are unchanged MAY also be included. If the unchanged instances are not included, they will remain associated with the LSP.</t>

      <t>If a PCE requires a PCC to allocate a (or several) specific binding
      value(s), it may do so by sending a PCUpd or PCInitiate message
      containing a TE-PATH-BINDING TLV(s). If the value(s) can be successfully
      allocated, the PCC reports the binding value(s) to the PCE. If the PCC
      considers the binding value specified by the PCE invalid, it MUST send a
      PCErr message with Error-Type = TBD2 ("Binding label/SID failure") and
      Error Value = TBD3 ("Invalid SID"). If the binding value is valid, but
      the PCC is unable to allocate the binding value, it MUST send a PCErr
      message with Error-Type = TBD2 ("Binding label/SID failure") and Error
      Value = TBD4 ("Unable to allocate the specified binding value"). Note
      that, in case of an error, the PCC rejects the PCUpd or PCInitiate
      message in its entirety and can include the offending TE-PATH-BINDING
      TLV in the PCEP-ERROR object.</t>

      <t>If a PCE wishes to request the withdrawal of a previously reported
      binding value, it MUST send a PCUpd message with the specific
      TE-PATH-BINDING TLV with R flag set to 1. If a PCE wishes to modify a
      previously requested binding value, it MUST request the withdrawal of
      the former binding value (with R flag set in the former TE-PATH-BINDING
      TLV) and include a new TE-PATH-BINDING TLV containing the new binding
      value. If a PCC receives a PCUpd message with TE-PATH-BINDING TLV where the R flag is set to 1, but either the binding value is missing (empty TE-PATH-BINDING TLV) or the binding value is incorrect, it MUST send a PCErr message with Error-Type = TBD2
   ("Binding label/SID failure") and Error Value = TBD6 ("Unable to
   remove the binding value"). </t>

      <!--<t>If a PCC wishes to withdraw all previously reported binding values, it 
   MUST send a PCRpt message without any TE-PATH-BINDING TLV.  If a
   PCC wishes to modify any or all previously reported binding values, it
   MUST send a PCRpt message containing TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs
   containing all the binding values that apply from that point on.</t>

   <t>If a PCE wishes to modify a previously requested binding value, it 
   MUST send a PCUpd message with TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs containing
   all the binding values that apply from that point on.  The absence of
   TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in PCUpd message means that the PCE does
   not specify a binding value. Any previously allocated binding values are considered to be requested to be withdrawn by the PCE.</t>-->

      <!--<t>The absence of TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in PCUpd message means
      that the PCE does not specify a binding value in which case any previous allocated binding values are withdraw.</t>-->

      <!--<t>If a PCC receives a new valid binding value from the PCE, it MUST try to allocate the new binding value. 
        If a PCC does not receive an former binding value for the PCE, it MUST withdraw the former binding value. 
      If the new binding value is successfully allocated, the PCC MUST report
      the new value to the PCE. Otherwise, it MUST send a PCErr message with
      Error-Type = TBD2 ("Binding label/SID failure") and Error Value = TBD4
      ("Unable to allocate the specified binding value"). Note that, all instances of TE-PATH-BINDING TLV that remains unchanged are always included in the LSP object and the offending TE-PATH-BINDING TLV is included in the PCEP-ERROR object.</t>-->

      <t>In some cases, a stateful PCE may want to request that the PCC
      allocate a binding value of the PCC's own choosing. It instructs the PCC
      by sending a PCUpd message containing an empty TE-PATH-BINDING TLV,
      i.e., no binding value is specified (bringing the Length field of the
      TLV to 4). A PCE can also request a PCC to allocate a binding value at
      the time of initiation by sending a PCInitiate message with an empty
      TE-PATH-BINDING TLV. Only one such instance of empty TE-PATH-BINDING TLV, per BT, SHOULD be included in the LSP object and others ignored on receipt. If
      the PCC is unable to allocate a new binding value as per the specified
      BT, it MUST send a PCErr message with Error-Type = TBD2 ("Binding
      label/SID failure") and Error-Value = TBD5 ("Unable to allocate a new
      binding label/SID").</t>

      <t>As previously noted, if a message contains an invalid TE-PATH-BINDING
      TLV that leads to an error condition, the whole message is rejected
      including any other valid instances of TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs, if any. The
      resulting error message MAY include the offending TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in
      the PCEP-ERROR object.</t>

      <t>If a PCC receives a TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in any message other than
      PCUpd or PCInitiate, it MUST close the corresponding PCEP session with
      the reason "Reception of a malformed PCEP message" (according to <xref
      target="RFC5440"/>). Similarly, if a PCE receives a TE-PATH-BINDING TLV
      in any message other than a PCRpt or if the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV is
      associated with any object other than an LSP or PCEP-ERROR object, the
      PCE MUST close the corresponding PCEP session with the reason "Reception
      of a malformed PCEP message" (according to <xref
      target="RFC5440"/>).</t>

      <t>If a TE-PATH-BINDING TLV is absent in the PCRpt message and no
      binding values were reported before, the PCE MUST assume that the
      corresponding LSP does not have any binding. Similarly, if
      TE-PATH-BINDING TLV is absent in the PCUpd message and no binding values
      were reported before, the PCC's local policy dictates how the binding
      allocations are made for a given LSP.</t>

      <t>Note that some binding types have similar information but different binding value formats. For example, BT=(2 or 3) is used for the SRv6 SID and BT=(0 or 1) is used for the MPLS Label. In case a PCEP speaker receives multiple TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs with the same SRv6 SID or MPLS Label but different BT values, it MUST send a PCErr message with Error-Type = TBD2 ("Binding
      label/SID failure") and Error-Value = TBD7 ("Inconsistent binding types").</t> 
    </section>

    <section anchor="SR-ERO" title="Binding SID in SR-ERO">
      <t>In PCEP messages, LSP route information is carried in the Explicit
      Route Object (ERO), which consists of a sequence of subobjects. <xref
      target="RFC8664"/> defines the "SR-ERO subobject" capable of carrying a
      SID as well as the identity of the node/adjacency (NAI) represented by
      the SID. The NAI Type (NT) field indicates the type and format of the
      NAI contained in the SR-ERO. In case of binding SID, the NAI MUST NOT be
      included and NT MUST be set to zero. <xref target="RFC8664"/> Section
      5.2.1 specifies bit settings and error handling in the case when NT=0.
      <!--So as per
      Section 5.2.1 of <xref target="RFC8664"/>, for NT=0, the F bit is set to
      1, the S bit needs to be zero and the Length is 8. Further, the M bit is
      set. If these conditions are not met, the entire ERO MUST be considered
      invalid and a PCErr message is sent by the PCC with Error-Type = 10
      ("Reception of an invalid object") and Error-Value = 11 ("Malformed
      object").--></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="SRv6-ERO" title="Binding SID in SRv6-ERO">
      <!--<t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing-ipv6"/> defines a new ERO
      subobject "SRv6-ERO subobject" for an SRv6 SID. As stated in <xref
      target="SR-ERO"/>, in case of binding SID, the NAI is not included and
      NT is set to zero i.e., NT=0, the F bit is set to 1, the S bit needs to
      be zero and the Length is 24 <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing-ipv6"/>. As per <xref
      target="RFC8664"/>, if these conditions are not met, the entire ERO is
      considered invalid and a PCErr message is sent by the PCC with
      Error-Type = 10 ("Reception of an invalid object") and Error-Value = 11
      ("Malformed object").</t>-->

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing-ipv6"/> defines the
      "SRv6-ERO subobject" for an SRv6 SID. Similarly to SR-ERO (<xref
      target="SR-ERO"/>), the NAI MUST NOT be included and the NT MUST be set
      to zero. <xref target="RFC8664"/> Section 5.2.1 specifies bit settings
      and error handling in the case when NT=0.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="PCECC" title="PCE Allocation of Binding label/SID"
             toc="default">
      <t><xref target="Operation"/> already includes the scenario where a PCE
      requires a PCC to allocate a specified binding value by sending a PCUpd
      or PCInitiate message containing a TE-PATH-BINDING TLV. This section
      specifies an OPTIONAL feature for the PCE to allocate the binding
      label/SID of its own accord in the case where the PCE also controls the
      label space of the PCC and can make the label allocation on its own as
      described in <xref target="RFC8283"/>. Note that the act of requesting a
      specific binding value (<xref target="Operation"/>) is different from
      the act of allocating a binding label/SID as described in this
      section.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC8283"/> introduces the architecture for PCE as a
      central controller as an extension of the architecture described in
      <xref target="RFC4655"/> and assumes the continued use of PCEP as the
      protocol used between PCE and PCC. <xref target="RFC9050"/> specifies
      the procedures and PCEP extensions for using the PCE as the central
      controller. It assumes that the exclusive label range to be used by a PCE is known and set on both PCEP peers.  A future extension could add the capability to advertise this range via a possible PCEP extension as
      well (see <xref target="I-D.li-pce-controlled-id-space"/>).</t>

      <t>When PCECC operations are supported as per <xref target="RFC9050"/>,
      the binding label/SID MAY also be allocated by the PCE itself. Both
      peers need to exchange the PCECC capability as described in <xref
      target="RFC9050"/> before the PCE can allocate the binding label/SID on
      its own.</t>

      <t>A new P flag in the LSP object <xref target="RFC8231"/> is introduced
      to indicate that the allocation needs to be made by the PCE. Note that the P flag could be used for other types of allocations (such as path segments <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-sr-path-segment"/>) in future. <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>P (PCE-allocated binding label/SID): If the bit is set to 1, it
          indicates that the PCC requests PCE to make allocations for this
          LSP. The TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in the LSP object identifies that the
          allocation is for a binding label/SID. A PCC MUST set this bit to 1
          and include a TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in the LSP object if it wishes to
          request for allocation of binding label/SID by the PCE in the PCEP
          message. A PCE MUST also set this bit to 1 and include a
          TE-PATH-BINDING TLV to indicate that the binding label/SID is
          allocated by PCE and encoded in the PCEP message towards the PCC.
          Further, if the binding label/SID is allocated by the PCC, 
          the PCE MUST set this bit to 0 and follow the procedure described in <xref
          target="Operation"/>.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Note that - <list style="symbols">
          <t>A PCE could allocate the binding label/SID of its own accord for
          a PCE-initiated or delegated LSP, and inform the PCC in the
          PCInitiate message or PCUpd message by setting P=1 and including
          TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in the LSP object.</t>

          <t>To let the PCC allocate the binding label/SID, a PCE MUST set P=0
          and include an empty TE-PATH-BINDING TLV ( i.e., no binding value is
          specified) in the LSP object in PCInitiate/PCUpd message.</t>

          <t>To request that the PCE allocate the binding label/SID, a PCC
          MUST set P=1, D=1, and include an empty TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in PCRpt
          message. The PCE SHOULD allocate it and respond to the PCC with
          PCUpd message including the allocated binding label/SID in the
          TE-PATH-BINDING TLV and P=1, D=1 in the LSP object. If the PCE is
          unable to allocate, it MUST send a PCErr message with Error-Type =
          TBD2 ("Binding label/SID failure") and Error-Value = TBD5 ("Unable
          to allocate a new binding label/SID").</t>

          <t>If one or both speakers (PCE and PCC) have not indicated support
          and willingness to use the PCEP extensions for the PCECC as per
          <xref target="RFC9050"/> and a PCEP peer receives P=1 in the LSP
          object, it MUST: <list style="symbols">
              <t>send a PCErr message with Error-Type=19 (Invalid Operation)
              and Error-value=16 (Attempted PCECC operations when PCECC
              capability was not advertised) and</t>

              <t>terminate the PCEP session.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>A legacy PCEP speaker that does not recognize the P flag in the
          LSP object would ignore it in accordance with <xref
          target="RFC8231"/>.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>It is assumed that the label range to be used by a PCE is known and
      set on both PCEP peers. The exact mechanism is out of the scope of <xref
      target="RFC9050"/> or this document. Note that the specific BSID could
      be from the PCE-controlled or the PCC-controlled label space. The PCE
      can directly allocate the label from the PCE-controlled label space
      using P=1 as described above, whereas the PCE can request the allocation
      of a specific BSID from the PCC-controlled label space with P=0 as
      described in <xref target="Operation"/>.</t>

      <!--<t>A PCC would set this bit to 1 (and carry the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-binding-label-sid"/> in the LSP object) to request for
      allocation of the binding label by the PCE in the PCReq or PCRpt
      message.  A PCE would also set this bit to 1 to indicate that the
      binding label is allocated by PCE and encoded in the PCRep,
      PCUpd, or PCInitiate message (the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV is present in
      LSP object).  Further, a PCE would set this bit to 0 to indicate
      that the allocation is done by the PCC instead.</t>-->

      <!--<t>The ingress PCC could request the binding label to be allocated by the PCE
   via a PCRpt message as per <xref target="RFC8231"/>.  The delegate flag (D-flag) MUST
   also be set for this LSP.  The TE-PATH-BINDING TLV MUST be included with no Binding
   Value. The PCECC would allocate the binding label and further respond to
   ingress PCC with PCUpd message as per <xref target="RFC8231"/> and MUST include the
   TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in an LSP object.  The P flag in the LSP object would be set to 1 to indicate that the allocation is made by the PCE.</t>-->

      <!--<t>The PCE could allocate the binding label on its own accord for a PCE-
   Initiated (or delegated) LSP.  The allocated binding label needs to be
   informed to the PCC.  The PCE would use the
   PCInitiate message <xref target="RFC8281"/> or PCUpd message <xref target="RFC8231"/> towards the
   PCC and MUST include the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in the LSP object. The P flag in the LSP object would be set to 1 to indicate that the allocation is made by the PCE.</t>  -->

      <!--<t>Before a PCE can allocate a binding label the PCECC capability MUST be exchanged on the PCEP session. Note that the CCI object is not used for binding allocation; this is done to maintain consistency with the rest of the binding label/SID procedures as per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-binding-label-sid"/>.</t>-->
    </section>

    <section anchor="Imp" title="Implementation Status">
      <t>[Note to the RFC Editor - remove this section before publication, as
      well as remove the reference to RFC 7942.]</t>

      <t>This section records the status of known implementations of the
      protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of this
      Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in <xref
      target="RFC7942"/>. The description of implementations in this section
      is intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in progressing
      drafts to RFCs. Please note that the listing of any individual
      implementation here does not imply endorsement by the IETF. Furthermore,
      no effort has been spent to verify the information presented here that
      was supplied by IETF contributors. This is not intended as, and must not
      be construed to be, a catalog of available implementations or their
      features. Readers are advised to note that other implementations may
      exist.</t>

      <t>According to <xref target="RFC7942"/>, "this will allow reviewers and
      working groups to assign due consideration to documents that have the
      benefit of running code, which may serve as evidence of valuable
      experimentation and feedback that have made the implemented protocols
      more mature. It is up to the individual working groups to use this
      information as they see fit".</t>

      <section anchor="Huawei" title="Huawei">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Organization: Huawei</t>

            <t>Implementation: Huawei's Router and Controller</t>

            <t>Description: An experimental code-point is used and will be
            modified to the value allocated in this document.</t>

            <t>Maturity Level: Production</t>

            <t>Coverage: Full</t>

            <t>Contact: c.l@huawei.com</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Cisco" title="Cisco">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Organization: Cisco Systems</t>

            <t>Implementation: Head-end and controller.</t>

            <t>Description: An experimental code-point is used and will be
            modified to the value allocated in this document.</t>

            <t>Maturity Level: Production</t>

            <t>Coverage: Full</t>

            <t>Contact: mkoldych@cisco.com</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations described in <xref target="RFC5440"/>,
      <xref target="RFC8231"/>, <xref target="RFC8281"/>, <xref
      target="RFC8664"/>, and  <xref target="RFC9050"/> are applicable to this specification. No additional
      security measure is required.</t>

<t>As described in <xref target="RFC8402"/> and <xref target="RFC8664"/>, SR intrinsically involves an entity (whether head-end or a central network controller) controlling and instantiating paths in the network without the involvement of (other) nodes along those paths.  Binding SIDs are in effect shorthand aliases for longer path representations, and the alias expansion is in principle known only by the node that acts on it.  In this document,
the expansion of the alias is shared between PCC and PCE, and rogue
actions by either PCC or PCE could result in shifting or misdirecting
traffic in ways that are hard for other nodes to detect.  In
particular, when a PCE propagates paths of the form {A, B, BSID} to
other entities, the BSID values are opaque, and a rogue PCE can
substitute a BSID from a different LSP in such paths to move traffic
without the recipient of the path knowing the ultimate destination.</t>



      <!--<t>As described in <xref target="RFC8664"/>, SR allows a network
      controller to instantiate and control paths in the network. A rogue PCE
      can manipulate binding SID allocations to move traffic around for some
      other LSP that uses BSID in its SR-ERO. Note that path {A, B, BSID} can
      be misdirected just by assigning the BSID value to a different LSP
      making it a lot easier to misdirect traffic (and harder to detect).</t>-->

<t>The case of BT=3 provides additional opportunities for malfeasance, as
it purports to convey information about internal SRv6 SID structure.
There is no mechanism defined to validate this internal structure
information, and mischaracterizing the division of bits into locator
block, locator node, function, and argument can result in different
interpretation of the bits by PCC and PCE.  Most notably, shifting bits
into or out of the "argument" is a direct vector for affecting
processing, but other attacks are also possible.</t>

      <!--<t>Note that in case of BT as 3, the manipulation of SID structure could
      be exploited by falsifying the various length values.</t>-->

      <t>Thus, as per <xref target="RFC8231"/>, it is RECOMMENDED that these
      PCEP extensions only be activated on authenticated and encrypted
      sessions across PCEs and PCCs belonging to the same administrative
      authority, using Transport Layer Security (TLS) <xref
      target="RFC8253"/>, as per the recommendations and best current
      practices in BCP195 <xref target="RFC7525"/> (unless explicitly set
      aside in <xref target="RFC8253"/>).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Manageability Considerations" toc="default">
      <t>All manageability requirements and considerations listed in <xref
      format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC5440"/>, <xref
      format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref
      target="RFC8664"/> apply to PCEP protocol extensions defined in this
      document. In addition, requirements and considerations listed in this
      section apply.</t>

      <section title="Control of Function and Policy" toc="default">
        <t>A PCC implementation SHOULD allow the operator to configure the
        policy the PCC needs to apply when allocating the binding
        label/SID.</t>

        <t>If BT is set to 2, the operator needs to have local policy set to decide
        the SID structure and the SRv6 Endpoint Behavior of the BSID.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Information and Data Models" toc="default">
        <t>The PCEP YANG module <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang"/> will
        be extended to include policy configuration for binding label/SID
        allocation.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Liveness Detection and Monitoring" toc="default">
        <t>The mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new
        liveness detection and monitoring requirements in addition to those
        already listed in <xref format="default" pageno="false"
        target="RFC5440"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Verify Correct Operations" toc="default">
        <t>The mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new
        operation verification requirements in addition to those already
        listed in <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC5440"/>,
        <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref
        target="RFC8664"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements On Other Protocols" toc="default">
        <t>The mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new
        requirements on other protocols.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Impact On Network Operations" toc="default">
        <t>The mechanisms defined in <xref format="default" pageno="false"
        target="RFC5440"/>, <xref format="default" pageno="false"
        target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref target="RFC8664"/> also apply to the
        PCEP extensions defined in this document.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA maintains the "Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers"
      registry. This document requests IANA actions to allocate code points
      for the protocol elements defined in this document.</t>

      <section anchor="TLV" title="PCEP TLV Type Indicators">
        <t>This document defines a new PCEP TLV; IANA is requested to confirm
        the following early allocations from the "PCEP TLV Type Indicators"
        subregistry of the PCEP Numbers registry, as follows:</t>

        <texttable anchor="TLV-Type" style="none" suppress-title="true">
          <ttcol align="center" width="15%">Value</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="left" width="30%">Description</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="left" width="55%">Reference</ttcol>

          <c/>

          <c>&nbsp;</c>

          <c/>

          <c>55</c>

          <c>TE-PATH-BINDING</c>

          <c>This document</c>
        </texttable>

        <section anchor="IANA-TLV" title="TE-PATH-BINDING TLV ">
          <t>IANA is requested to create a new subregistry "TE-PATH-BINDING
          TLV BT field" to manage the value of the Binding Type field in the
          TE-PATH-BINDING TLV. Initial values for the subregistry are given
          below. New values are assigned by Standards Action <xref
          target="RFC8126"/>.</t>

          <texttable anchor="BT" style="none" suppress-title="true">
            <ttcol align="center" width="15%">Value</ttcol>

            <ttcol align="left" width="30%">Description</ttcol>

            <ttcol align="left" width="55%">Reference</ttcol>

            <c/>

            <c>&nbsp;</c>

            <c/>

            <c>0</c>

            <c>MPLS Label</c>

            <c>This document</c>

            <c>1</c>

            <c>MPLS Label Stack Entry</c>

            <c>This document</c>

            <c>2</c>

            <c>SRv6 SID</c>

            <c>This document</c>

            <c>3</c>

            <c>SRv6 SID with Behavior and Structure</c>

            <c>This document</c>

            <c>4-255</c>

            <c>Unassigned</c>

            <c>This document</c>
          </texttable>

          <t>IANA is requested to create a new subregistry "TE-PATH-BINDING
          TLV Flag field" to manage the Flag field in the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV.
          New values are to be assigned by Standards Action <xref
          target="RFC8126"/>. Each bit should be tracked with the following
          qualities:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Bit number (count from 0 as the most significant bit)</t>

              <t>Description</t>

              <t>Reference</t>
            </list></t>

          <texttable anchor="BF" style="none" suppress-title="true">
            <ttcol align="center" width="15%">Bit</ttcol>

            <ttcol align="left" width="30%">Description</ttcol>

            <ttcol align="left" width="55%">Reference</ttcol>

            <c/>

            <c>&nbsp;</c>

            <c/>

            <!--<c>7</c>

            <c>Specified-BSID-Only Flag (S-Flag)</c>

            <c>This document</c>

            <c>6</c>

            <c>Drop Upon Invalid Flag (I-Flag)</c>

            <c>This document</c>-->

            <c>0</c>

            <c>R (Removal)</c>

            <c>This document</c>

            <c>1-7</c>

            <c>Unassigned</c>

            <c>This document</c>
          </texttable>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="LSP" title="LSP Object">
        <t>IANA is requested to confirm the early allocation for a new
        code-point in the "LSP Object Flag Field" sub-registry for the new P
        flag as follows:</t>

        <texttable anchor="LSP-Flag" style="none" suppress-title="true">
          <ttcol align="center" width="15%">Bit</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="left" width="30%">Description</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="left" width="55%">Reference</ttcol>

          <c/>

          <c>&nbsp;</c>

          <c/>

          <c>0</c>

          <c>PCE-allocated binding label/SID</c>

          <c>This document</c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Error-Type" title="PCEP Error Type and Value">
        <t>This document defines a new Error-type and associated Error-Values
        for the PCErr message. IANA is requested to allocate new error-type
        and error-values within the "PCEP-ERROR Object Error Types and Values"
        subregistry of the PCEP Numbers registry, as follows:</t>

        <texttable anchor="Error" style="none" suppress-title="true">
          <ttcol align="center" width="10%">Error-Type</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="left" width="30%">Meaning</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="left" width="50%">Error-value</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="left" width="10%">Reference</ttcol>

          <c/>

          <c>&nbsp;</c>

          <c/>

          <c/>

          <c>TBD2</c>

          <c>Binding label/SID failure</c>

          <c>&nbsp;0: Unassigned</c>

          <c>This document</c>

          <c>&nbsp;</c>

          <c>&nbsp;</c>

          <c>TBD3: Invalid SID</c>

          <c>This document</c>

          <c>&nbsp;</c>

          <c>&nbsp;</c>

          <c>TBD4: Unable to allocate the specified binding value</c>

          <c>This document</c>

          <c>&nbsp;</c>

          <c>&nbsp;</c>

          <c>TBD5: Unable to allocate a new binding label/SID</c>

          <c>This document</c>
          <c>&nbsp;</c>

          <c>&nbsp;</c>

          <c>TBD6: Unable to remove the binding value</c>

          <c>This document</c>    
          <c>&nbsp;</c>

          <c>&nbsp;</c>

          <c>TBD7: Inconsistent binding types</c>

          <c>This document</c>                      
        </texttable>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgement" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We would like to thank Milos Fabian, Mrinmoy Das, Andrew Stone, Tom
      Petch, Aijun Wang, Olivier Dugeon, and Adrian Farrel for their valuable
      comments.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Julien Meuric for shepherding. Thanks to John Scudder for
      the AD review.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Theresa Enghardt for the GENART review.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Martin Vigoureux, Benjamin Kaduk, and Eric Vyncke for the IESG reviews.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3032.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5440.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5462.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7525.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7942.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8231.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8253.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8281.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8402.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8664.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8986.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9050.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing-ipv6"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!--<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4206.xml"?>-->

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4655.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8283.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8669.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing-policy"?>

      <!--<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-segment-routing-te-policy"?>-->

      <!--<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-isis-segment-routing-extensions"?>-->

      <!--<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller"?>-->

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.li-pce-controlled-id-space"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pce-sr-path-segment"?>
    </references>

    <!--<section anchor="sec_pcecc" title="PCE based Central Controller">
  <t><xref target="RFC8283"/> introduces the architecture for PCE as a central controller
   as an extension of the architecture described in <xref target="RFC4655"/> and
   assumes the continued use of PCEP as the protocol used between PCE
   and PCC.  <xref target="RFC8283"/>  further examines the motivations and
   applicability for PCEP as a Southbound Interface (SBI), and
   introduces the implications for the protocol.</t>
   <t>As per <xref target="RFC8283"/>, PCE as a central controller can allocate and
   provision the node/prefix/adjacency label (SID) via PCEP. It can also be used to allocate the binding SID as described in this section.</t> 


   <t>The PCECC Capability as per
   <xref target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/> should also be
   advertised on the PCEP session, along with the SR sub-TLVs before using this procedure.</t>

   <t>A P flag in LSP object is introduced in <xref target="I-D.li-pce-sr-path-segment"/> to indicate the allocation needs to be made by the PCE. The same flag is also set for the binding SID allocation request. A PCC would set this bit to 1 to request for
      allocation of the binding label/SID by the PCE in the PCReq or PCRpt
      message.  A PCE would also set this bit to 1 to indicate that the
      binding label/SID is allocated by PCE and encoded in the PCRep,
      PCUpd or PCInitiate message (the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV is present in
      LSP object).  Further, a PCE would set this bit to 0 to indicate
      that the path identifier is allocated by the PCC as described above.</t>

   <t>The ingress PCC could request the binding label/SID to be allocated by the PCE
   via PCRpt message as per <xref target="RFC8231"/>.  The delegate flag (D-flag) MUST
   also be set for this LSP.  The TE-PATH-BINDING TLV MAY be included with no Binding
   Value. The PCECC would allocated the binding label/SID and further respond to
   Ingress PCC with PCUpd message as per <xref target="RFC8231"/> and MUST include the
   TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in a LSP object.  The P flag in the LSP object would be set to 1 to indicate that the allocation is made by the PCE.</t>

   <t>The PCE could allocate the binding label/SID on its own accord for a PCE-
   Initiated (or delegated LSP).  The allocated binding label/SID needs to be
   informed to the PCC.  The PCE would use the
   PCInitiate message <xref target="RFC8281"/> or PCUpd message <xref target="RFC8231"/> towards the
   PCC and MUST include the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in the LSP object. The P flag in the LSP object would be set to 1 to indicate that the allocation is made by the PCE.</t>  

 </section> -->

    <section title="Contributor Addresses" toc="default">
      <t><figure align="left" alt="" height="" suppress-title="false" title=""
          width="">
          <artwork align="left" alt="" height="" name="" type="" width=""
                   xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
Jonathan Hardwick
Metaswitch Networks
33 Genotin Road
Enfield
United Kingdom

EMail: Jonathan.Hardwick@metaswitch.com


Dhruv Dhody
Huawei Technologies
Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield
Bangalore, Karnataka  560066
India

EMail: dhruv.ietf@gmail.com

Mahendra Singh Negi
RtBrick India
N-17L, Floor-1, 18th Cross Rd, HSR Layout Sector-3
Bangalore, Karnataka  560102
India

EMail: mahend.ietf@gmail.com

Mike Koldychev
Cisco Systems, Inc.
2000 Innovation Drive
Kanata, Ontario  K2K 3E8
Canada

Email: mkoldych@cisco.com

Zafar Ali
Cisco Systems, Inc.

Email: zali@cisco.com
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
