<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-li-pce-sr-path-segment-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Path ID in PCEP">Path Computation Element Communication
    Protocol (PCEP) Extension for Path Identification in Segment Routing
    (SR)</title>

    <author fullname="Cheng Li" initials="C." surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>chengli13@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mach(Guoyi) Chen" initials="M." surname="Chen">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>Mach.chen@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jie Dong" initials="J." surname="Dong">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>jie.dong@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Zhenbin Li" initials="Z." surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>lizhenbin@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dhruv Dhody" initials="D" surname="Dhody">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560066</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dhruv.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="20" month="June" year="2018"/>

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>PCE Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Path Computation Element (PCE) provides path computation
      functions in support of traffic engineering in Multiprotocol Label
      Switching (MPLS) and Generalized MPLS (GMPLS) networks.</t>

      <t>The Source Packet Routing in Networking (SPRING) architecture
      describes how Segment Routing (SR) can be used to steer packets through
      an IPv6 or MPLS network using the source routing paradigm. A Segment
      Routed Path can be derived from a variety of mechanisms, including an
      IGP Shortest Path Tree (SPT), explicit configuration, or a Path
      Computation Element (PCE).</t>

      <t>Path identification is needed for several use cases such as
      performance measurement in Segment Routing (SR) network. This document
      specifies extensions to the Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) to
      support requesting, replying, reporting and updating the path identifier
      between PCEP speakers.</t>

      <t/>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when,
      they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="RFC5440"/> describes the Path Computation Element (PCE)
      Communication Protocol (PCEP). PCEP enables the communication between a
      Path Computation Client (PCC) and a PCE, or between PCE and PCE, for the
      purpose of computation of Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) as well
      as Generalzied MPLS (GMPLS) Traffic Engineering Label Switched Path (TE
      LSP) characteristics.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC8231"/> specifies a set of extensions to PCEP to
      enable stateful control of TE LSPs within and across PCEP sessions in
      compliance with <xref target="RFC4657"/>. It includes mechanisms to
      effect LSP State Synchronization between PCCs and PCEs, delegation of
      control over LSPs to PCEs, and PCE control of timing and sequence of
      path computations within and across PCEP sessions. The model of
      operation where LSPs are initiated from the PCE is described in <xref
      target="RFC8281"/>.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller"/>
      specify the procedures and PCEP protocol extensions for using the PCE as
      the central controller for static LSPs, where LSPs can be provisioned as
      explicit label instructions at each hop on the end-to-end path.</t>

      <t>Segment routing (SR) <xref target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing"/>
      leverages the source routing and tunneling paradigms. SR supports
      steering packets into an explicit forwarding path according to the
      Segment Routing Policy ( SR Policy) <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing-policy"/> at the ingress
      node.</t>

      <t>An SR path needs to be identified in some use cases such as
      performance measurement. For identifying an SR path, <xref
      target="I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment"/> introduces a new segment
      that is referred to as Path Segment. <xref
      target="I-D.li-idr-sr-policy-path-segment-distribution"/> defines
      extensions to BGP to distribute SR policies carrying Path segment
      identifier.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/> specifies extensions to
      the Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) <xref target="RFC5440"/>
      for SR networks, that allow a stateful PCE to compute and initiate SR-TE
      paths, as well as a PCC to request, report or delegate SR paths. <xref
      target="I-D.negi-pce-segment-routing-ipv6"/> extend PCEP to support SR
      for IPv6 data plane.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/>
      specifies the procedures and PCEP protocol extensions when a PCE-based
      controller is also responsible for configuring the forwarding actions on
      the routers (SR SID distribution in this case), in addition to computing
      the paths for packet flows in a segment routing network and telling the
      edge routers what instructions to attach to packets as they enter the
      network.</t>

      <t>This document specifies a mechanism to carry the SR path
      identification information in PCEP messages <xref target="RFC5440"/>
      <xref target="RFC8231"/> <xref target="RFC8281"/>. The path ID can be a
      path segment in SR-MPLS <xref
      target="I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment"/>, or a path ID in SRv6
      <xref target="I-D.li-spring-passive-pm-for-srv6-np"/>, or other IDs that
      can identify the SR path. This document also extends the PCECC-SR
      mechanism to inform the path ID to the egress PCC.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This memo makes use of the terms defined in <xref target="RFC4655"/>,
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/>, and <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview of Path ID Extensions in PCEP">
      <t>This document specifies a mechanism of encoding (and allocating) path
      ID (path segment in case of MPLS, path ID in case of IPv6, etc) in PCEP
      extensions. For supporting path ID in PCEP, several TLVs and flags are
      defined. The formats of the objects and TLVs are described in <xref
      target="obj"/>. The procedures of path ID allocation are described in
      <xref target="pro"/>.</t>

      <t>There are various modes of operations, such as - <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>The path ID can be allocated by Ingress PCC itself and informed
          to the PCE. The PCE can then inform the egress PCC.</t>

          <t>The PCC can also request PCE to allocate the path ID, in this
          case, the PCE would allocate and inform the assigned path ID to the
          ingress/egress PCC using PCEP messages.</t>

          <t>For PCE can allocate a path ID on its own accord and inform the
          ingress/egress PCC , useful for PCE-initiated LSPs.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The path ID information to the ingress PCC and PCE is exchanged via
      an extension to <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/> and <xref
      target="I-D.negi-pce-segment-routing-ipv6"/>. The path ID information to
      the egress PCC is informed via an extension to the PCECC-SR procedures
      <xref target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/>.</t>

      <t>For the PCE to allocate a path ID, the PCE MUST be aware of the path
      ID space from the PCCs. This is done via mechanism as described in <xref
      target="I-D.li-pce-controlled-id-space"/>.</t>

      <t>[Editor's note - There is currently no mechanism for the PCE to ask
      PCC to allocate path ID. Further discussion is needed to check if that
      would be useful in any way.]</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="obj" title="Objects and TLVs">
      <t/>

      <section title="The OPEN Object">
        <section title="The SR PCE Capability sub-TLV">
          <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/> defined a new Path
          Setup Type (PST) and SR-PCE-CAPABILITY sub-TLV for SR. PCEP speakers
          use this sub-TLV to exchange information about their SR capability.
          The TLV includes a Flags field and one bit (L-flag) was allocated in
          <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/>.</t>

          <t>This document adds an additional flag for path ID allocation, as
          follows - <list>
              <t>P (Path Identification bit): A PCEP speaker sets this flag to
              1 to indicate that it has the capability to encode SR path
              identification (path segment, as per <xref
              target="I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment"/>).</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="The SRv6 PCE Capability sub-TLV">
          <t><xref target="I-D.negi-pce-segment-routing-ipv6"/> defined a new
          Path Setup Type (PST) and SRv6-PCE-CAPABILITY sub-TLV for SRv6. PCEP
          speakers use this sub-TLV to exchange information about their SRv6
          capability. The TLV includes a Flags field and one bit (L-flag) was
          allocated in <xref target="I-D.negi-pce-segment-routing-ipv6"/>.</t>

          <t>This document adds an additional flag for path ID allocation, as
          follows - <list>
              <t>P (Path Identification bit): A PCEP speaker sets this flag to
              1 to indicate that it has the capability to encode SRv6 path
              identification.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="PCECC-CAPABILITY sub-TLV">
          <t>The PCECC Capability as per <xref
          target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/> MUST also
          be advertised on the egress PCEP session, along with the SR
          sub-TLVs. This is needed to ensure that the PCE can inform the
          egress PCC of the path ID via PCECC mechanism as described in this
          document.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="LSP Object ">
        <t>The LSP Object is defined in Section 7.3 of <xref
        target="RFC8231"/>. This document adds the following flags to the LSP
        Object: <list>
            <t>P (Path Identification Allocation bit): If the bit is set to 1,
            it indicates that the path identifier needs to be allocated by the
            PCE for this LSP. A PCC would set this bit to 1 to request for
            allocation of path identifier by the PCE in the PCReq or PCRpt
            message. A PCE would also set this bit to 1 to indicate that the
            path identifier is allocated by PCE and encoded in the PCRep,
            PCUpd or PCInitiate message (the PATH-ID TLV MUST be present in
            LSP object).</t>
          </list></t>

        <section anchor="path-id-tlv" title="Path ID TLV">
          <t>The PATH-ID TLV is an optional TLV for use in the LSP Object for
          path ID allocation. The type of this TLV is to be allocated by IANA.
          The format is shown below.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="fig1" title="The PATH-ID TLV Format">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|             Type              |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       IDT     |             Flags                       |E|C|L|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                             Path ID                           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                   

]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The type (16-bit) of the TLV is TBA (to be allocated by IANA).
          The length (16-bit) has a fixed value of 8 octets. The value
          contains the following fields: <list>
              <t>IDT (The ID type - 8 bits): The IDT field specifies the type
              of the Path ID field, which carries a Path ID corresponding to
              the SR path.<list style="symbols">
                  <t>0: MPLS Path segment, which is an MPLS label as defined
                  in <xref target="I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment"/>. The
                  PST type MUST be set to SR (MPLS).</t>

                  <t>1: SRv6 Path ID, which is a 4-octet integer as defined in
                  <xref target="I-D.li-spring-passive-pm-for-srv6-np"/>. The
                  PST type MUST be set to SRv6.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>Flags (24 bits): Three flag is currently defined: <list
                  style="symbols">
                  <t>L-Bit (Local/Global - 1 bit): If set, then the Path ID
                  carried by the PATH-ID TLV has local significance. If not
                  set, then the Path ID carried by this TLV has global
                  significance (i.e. Path ID is global within an SR
                  domain).</t>

                  <t>C-bit (PCC/PCE - 1 bit): If set, then the Path ID carried
                  by the PATH-ID TLV has been allocated by the PCC. If not
                  set, then the Path ID carried by this TLV has been allocated
                  by the PCE.</t>

                  <t>E-bit (Egress/Ingress - 1 bit): If set, then the Path ID
                  carried by the PATH-ID TLV has been allocated from the
                  Egress Path ID space. If not set, then the Path ID carried
                  by this TLV has been allocated from the Ingress Path ID
                  space.</t>

                  <t>The unassigned bits MUST be set to 0 and MUST be ignored
                  at receipt.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>Path ID: The path ID of an SR path. The path ID type is
              indicated by the ID Type field. It can be a path segment <xref
              target="I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment"/> in MPLS label
              format. Or it can be a 4 octets integer ID as defined in <xref
              target="I-D.li-spring-passive-pm-for-srv6-np"/> or other IDs
              that can identify a path.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Only one instance of each TLV is processed, if more than one TLV
          of each type is included, the first one is processed and others MUST
          be ignored.</t>

          <t>When the path ID allocation is enable, a PATH-ID TLV SHOULD be
          included in the LSP object.</t>

          <t>If the path ID is allocated by the ingress node, a PATH-ID TLV
          MUST be included in a LSP object (with C-bit set and E-bit is unset)
          in the PCEP message from PCC. In this case the P flag in LSP object
          is set to 0.</t>

          <t>If the PCC request the path ID to be allocated by the PCE, P flag
          in LSP object is set to 1 and Path ID TLV MAY be skipped. After the
          PCE has allocated a path ID, it MUST include the PATH-ID TLV in a
          LSP object (with C-bit unset), the E-bit is set by PCE based on the
          path ID space from which the allocation is made.</t>

          <t>If the PCE allocated the path ID on its own accord, a PATH-ID TLV
          MUST be included in a LSP object (with C-bit unset), the E-bit is
          set by PCE based on the path ID space from which the allocation is
          made.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="FEC Object">
        <t>The FEC Object <xref
        target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/> is used to
        specify the FEC information and MAY be carried within PCInitiate or
        PCRpt message for the PCECC-SR operations. The PCE MUST inform the
        Path Identification information to the Egress PCC. To do this, this
        document extends the procedures of <xref
        target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/> by defining a
        new FEC object type for Path.</t>

        <t>FEC Object-Type is TBD 'Path'.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="fig2" title="The path FEC object Format">
            <artwork><![CDATA[   
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
//                           TLV(s)                            //
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+   
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>One or more following TLV(s) are allowed in the 'path' FEC object -
        <list style="symbols">
            <t>SYMBOLIC-PATH-NAME TLV: As defined in <xref target="RFC8231"/>,
            it is a human-readable string that identifies an LSP in the
            network.</t>

            <t>LSP-IDENTIFIERS TLVs: As defined in <xref target="RFC8231"/>,
            it is optional for SR, but could be used to encode the source,
            destination and other identification information for the path.</t>

            <t>SPEAKER-ENTITY-ID TLV: As defined in <xref target="RFC8232"/>,
            a unique identifier for the PCEP speaker, it is used to identify
            the Ingress PCC.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Either SYMBOLIC-PATH-NAME TLV or LSP-IDENTIFIERS TLV MUST be
        included. SPEAKER-ENTITY-ID TLV is optional. Only one instance of each
        TLV is processed, if more than one TLV of each type is included, the
        first one is processed and others MUST be ignored.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="CCI Object">
        <t>The Central Control Instructions (CCI) Object is used by the PCE to
        specify the forwarding instructions is defined in <xref
        target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller"/>. Further
        <xref target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/> defined
        a CCI object type for SR.</t>

        <t>The Path ID information is encoded directly in the CCI SR object.
        The Path ID TLV as described in the <xref target="path-id-tlv"/>, MAY
        also be included in the CCI SR object.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="pro" title="Operations">
      <t>The path ID allocation and encoding is as per the stateful PCE
      operations for segment routing. The procedures are as per the
      corresponding extensions defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/> and <xref
      target="I-D.negi-pce-segment-routing-ipv6"/> (which are further based on
      <xref target="RFC8231"/> and <xref target="RFC8281"/>). The additional
      operations for path identification are defined in this section.</t>

      <t>To notify the path ID to the Egress PCC, the procedures are as per
      the PCECC-SR <xref
      target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/> (which is based
      on <xref target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller"/>). The
      additional operations are defined in this section.</t>

      <section title="PCC Allocated Path ID">
        <section anchor="Ingress" title="Ingress PCC Allocated Path ID">
          <t>The Ingress PCC could allocate the Path ID and inform the PCE via
          the PCRpt message as per <xref target="RFC8231"/>. The PATH-ID TLV
          MUST be included in a LSP object in the PCEP message from PCC. The P
          flag in LSP object is set to 0. On receiving this report, the PCE
          updates the information in its database. The active PCE (where the
          LSP is delegated) further informs the egress about the path ID
          allocated by the PCC using the PCInitiate message as described in
          <xref target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/>.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="fig3" title="Ingress PCC Allocated Path ID">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
                  Ingress                                    Egress     
                  +-+-+                +-+-+                 +-+-+
                  |PCC|                |PCE|                 |PCC|
                  +-+-+                +-+-+                 +-+-+
1) LSP State        | ----  PCRpt ---->  |                     |
   Delegate and     |     Delegate=1     |                     |              
   Inform the       |     PATH-ID TLV    |2) PCE update        |
   Path ID alloc    |                    |   the LSP-DB        |
   by PCC           |                    |                     |   
                    |3) PCE informs the  | --- PCInitiate ---> |
                    |   Path ID to Egress|     FEC=Path        |
                    |                    |                     |  
                    |                    | <-------- PCRpt --- |
                    |                    |                     |

]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="PCE Allocated Path ID">
        <section title="PCE Controlled ID Spaces Advertisement">
          <t>For allocating the path IDs to SR paths by the PCEs, the PCE
          controlled ID Spaces MUST be known at PCEs via configurations or any
          other mechanism. The PCE controlled ID spaces MAY be advertised as
          described in <xref target="I-D.li-pce-controlled-id-space"/>.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="PCE_1" title="Ingress PCC request Path ID to PCE">
          <t>The ingress PCC could request the path ID to be allocated by the
          PCE via PCRpt message as per <xref target="RFC8231"/>. The delegate
          flag (D-flag) MUST also be set for this LSP. The PATH-ID TLV MAY be
          included with Path ID set to 0x0000. The active PCE would allocated
          the path ID as per the PATH-ID flags and in case PATH-ID is not
          included, the PCE MUST act based on the local policy. The PCE would
          further respond to Ingress PCC with PCUpd message as per <xref
          target="RFC8231"/> and MUST include the PATH-ID TLV in a LSP object.
          The PCE would further inform the egress PCC about the path ID
          allocated by the PCE using the PCInitiate message as described in
          <xref target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/>.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="fig4" title="Ingress PCC request Path ID to PCE">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
                  Ingress                                    Egress     
                  +-+-+                +-+-+                 +-+-+
                  |PCC|                |PCE|                 |PCC|
                  +-+-+                +-+-+                 +-+-+
1) LSP State        | ----  PCRpt ---->  |                     |
   Delegate         |     Delegate=1     |                     |              
                    |     P=1            |2) PCE update        |
                    |                    |   the LSP-DB and    |
                    |                    |   allocate Path ID  |   
                    |<----  PCUpd ----   |3)Paths update with  |
                    |     PATH-ID TLV    |  Path ID            |
                    |                    |                     |
4) LSP State Report | -----  PCRpt --->  |                     |
                    |                    |                     | 
                    |5) PCE informs the  | --- PCInitiate ---> |
                    |   Path ID to Egress|     FEC=Path        |
                    |                    |                     |  
                    |                    | <-------- PCRpt --- |
                    |                    |                     |

]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="PCE_2" title="PCE allocated Path ID on its own">
          <t>The PCE could allocate the path ID on its own accord for a
          PCE-Initiated (or delegated LSP). The allocated path ID needs to be
          informed to the Ingress and Egress PCC. The PCE would use the
          PCInitiate message <xref target="RFC8281"/> or PCUpd message <xref
          target="RFC8231"/> towards the Ingress PCC and MUST include the
          PATH-ID TLV in the LSP object. The PCE would further inform the
          egress PCC about the path ID allocated by the PCE using the
          PCInitiate message as described in <xref
          target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/>.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="fig5" title="PCE allocated Path ID on its own">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
                  Ingress                                    Egress     
                  +-+-+                +-+-+                 +-+-+
                  |PCC|                |PCE|                 |PCC|
                  +-+-+                +-+-+                 +-+-+
                    |                    |                     |
                    | <--PCInitiate---   |1)Initiate LSP with  |
                    |    PATH-ID TLV     |  Path ID            |
                    |                    |                     |
 2)LSP delegation   |---PCRpt, D=1--->   | (Confirm)           |
                    |                    |                     | 
                    |3) PCE informs the  | --- PCInitiate ---> |
                    |   Path ID to Egress|     FEC=Path        |
                    |                    |                     |  
                    |                    | <-------- PCRpt --- |
                    |                    |                     |

]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Two Label Solution">
        <t><xref target="I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment"/> describe a Path
        Segment to uniquely identify an SR path in a specific context. (e.g.,
        in the context of the egress node or ingress node of an SR path, or
        within an SR domain). It further describes two solution based on 'one
        label' or 'two labels' solution. For the latter, two segments (Source
        segment and Path segment) are used to identify an SR path where the
        source segment is a global node segment which can uniquely identify a
        node within the SR domain (it is NOT used for forwarding and indicates
        that a Path segment immediately follows). The combination of Source
        segment and Path segment uniquely identify an SR Path with an SR
        domain.</t>

        <t>The procedure described in this document allocates and encode the
        Path Segment only. It is expected that the Egress PCC is aware of the
        Source segment by some other procedures. These procedures could be
        IGP, PCECC-SR, or some other mechanisms.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>TBA</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBA</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t/>

      <t/>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5440'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8231'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8232'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8281'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.negi-pce-segment-routing-ipv6'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.li-pce-controlled-id-space'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller'?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4655"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4657"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing-policy'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.li-spring-passive-pm-for-srv6-np'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.li-idr-sr-policy-path-segment-distribution'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
