<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="Yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-dhody-pce-stateful-pce-interdomain-06" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="STATEFUL-INTERDOMAIN">Stateful Path Computation 
    Element (PCE) Inter-domain Considerations</title>
    <author initials="D" surname="Dhody" fullname="Dhruv Dhody">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Divyasree Techno Park, Whitefield</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560066</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>dhruv.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	<author initials="X" surname="Zhang" fullname="Xian Zhang">
	<organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
	<address>
		<postal>
			<street>Bantian, Longgang District</street>
			<city>Shenzhen</city>
			<region/>
			<code>518129</code>
			<country>P.R.China</country>
		</postal>
		<email>zhang.xian@huawei.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>
    <date year="2018" />
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>PCE Working Group</workgroup>
    <abstract>
   <t> 
   A stateful Path Computation Element (PCE) maintains information about
   Label Switched Path (LSP) characteristics and resource usage within a
   network in order to provide traffic engineering path calculations for its
   associated Path Computation Clients (PCCs).  Furthermore, PCEs are used to
   compute shortest constrained Traffic Engineering Label
   Switched Paths (TE LSPs) in Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) and
   Generalized MPLS (GMPLS) networks across multiple domains.</t>
   
   <t>This document describes general considerations for the deployment of stateful PCE(s) 
     in inter-domain scenarios including inter-area and inter-AS. The inter-layer considerations
     will be described in a separate document. This document does not specify any extensions to	
 	   PCEP.</t>
   </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
   <t>The Path Computation Element communication Protocol (PCEP) provides
   mechanisms for Path Computation Elements (PCEs) to perform path
   computations in response to Path Computation Clients' (PCCs) requests.</t>

   <t><xref target='RFC8051'/> describes
   general considerations for a stateful PCE deployment and examines its
   applicability and benefits, as well as its challenges and limitations
   through a number of use cases.
   <xref target='RFC8231'/> describes a set of extensions to PCEP to
   provide stateful control.  A stateful PCE has access to not only the
   information carried by the network's Interior Gateway Protocol (IGP),
   but also the set of active paths and their reserved resources for its
   computations.  The additional state allows the PCE to compute
   constrained paths while considering individual LSPs and their
   interactions.</t>
   
   <t>The ability to compute shortest constrained TE LSPs in Multiprotocol
   Label Switching (MPLS) and Generalized MPLS (GMPLS) networks across
   multiple domains has been identified as a key motivation for PCE 
   development.  In this context, a domain is a collection of network elements within a common
   sphere of address management or path computational responsibility
   such as an Interior Gateway Protocol (IGP) area or an Autonomous
   Systems (AS).</t>   
   
   <t>This document presents general considerations for stateful PCE(s) deployment
   in multi-domain scenarios.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview" toc="default">
    <t>A stateful PCE maintains two sets of information for use in path
   computation.  The first is the Traffic Engineering Database (TED)
   which includes the topology and resource state in the network. 
   The second is the LSP State Database (LSP-DB), in which a PCE stores 
   attributes of all active LSPs in the network, such as their paths 
   through the network, bandwidth/resource usage, switching types and 
   LSP constraints.  This state information allows the PCE to compute 
   constrained paths while considering individual LSPs and their 
   inter-dependency. <xref target="RFC8231"/> applies 
   equally to MPLS-TE and GMPLS LSPs
   and distinguishes between an active and a passive stateful PCE. A
   passive stateful PCE uses LSP state information to optimize path
   computations but does not actively update LSP state.  In contrast, an
   active stateful PCE may issue recommendations to the network.  For
   example, an active stateful PCE may update LSP parameters for those
   LSPs that have been delegated control over to the PCE by its PCCs.</t>
   
   <t>The capability to compute the routes of end-to-end inter-domain 
   MPLS-TE LSPs is expressed as requirements in 
   <xref target="RFC4105"/> and <xref target="RFC4216"/> and may be 
   realized by PCE(s). PCEs may use one of the following mechanisms to 
   compute end-to-end paths: </t>
   <t>
   <list style="symbols"> 
   <t>a per-domain path computation technique <xref target="RFC5152"/>;</t>
   <t>a Backward-Recursive PCE-based Computation (BRPC) mechanism 
   <xref target="RFC5441"/>;</t>
   <t>a Hierarchical PCE mechanism <xref target="RFC6805"/>;</t>
   </list>
   </t>
   <t>This document examines the stateful PCE inter-domain considerations
   for all of these mechanisms.</t>
   <section title="LSP State Synchronization" toc="default">
   <t>The population of the LSP-DB using information received from PCCs
   (ingress LSR) is supported by the stateful PCE extensions defined in
   <xref target="RFC8231"/> , i.e., via LSP state 
   report messages.</t>
   <t>The inter-domain LSP state is synchronized to the ingress-PCE from 
     the ingress LSR (PCC), but this PCC cannot synchronize to other PCEs
     (in transit or egress domains), thus other mechanism must be investigated for
     this purpose.</t>

    <t>Either the boundary node of the other domains, would need to	
 	   synchronize the state of LSP passing though it to the PCE, or a	
 	   mechanism for synchronization of inter-domain LSPs between the PCEs	
 	   is required.  The former would require small change in the existing	
 	   state synchronization and reporting where a border node acts as a	
 	   PCC.  The later could use the mechanism described in	
 	   <xref target="I-D.litkowski-pce-state-sync"/> can be used between the PCEs to	
 	   synchronize the inter-domain LSP state between each other.  Further	
 	   section provide various considerations for this choice.</t>
   </section>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Stateful PCE Deployments" toc="default">
    <t>There are multiple models to perform PCE-based inter-domain path 
    computation: 
    <list style="symbols">
   <t>A single PCE</t>
   <t>Multiple PCEs
       <list style="symbols">
       <t>without inter-PCE communication</t>
       <t>with inter-PCE communication</t>
       </list></t>    
    </list></t>
    
   <t>This section describe stateful PCE considerations for each 
   of these deployment models.</t>   
     <section title="Single Stateful PCE, Multiple Domains" toc="default">
     <t>In this model, inter-domain path computation is 
     performed by a single stateful PCE that has topology visibility into all 
     domains. The inter-domain LSP state is synchronized to the PCE from 
     the ingress LSR (PCC) itself. The PCC may also choose to delegate 
     control over this LSP to the PCE. Thus this model is similar to a 
     single domain in all aspects.</t>
     
     <t>Following figure show an example of inter-area case comprising
     of Area 0,1 and 2. A single stateful PCE is deployed for all areas.
     </t>
     <figure>
     <artwork align='center'>
                         ******* 
                         * PCE *
                         ******* 
                
                !                      !
                !                      !  
A----B----C----ABR1----D----E----F----ABR2----G----H----I
|    |    |     |      |    |    |     |      |    |    |
|    |    |     |      |    |    |     |      |    |    |
J----K----L----ABR3----M----N----O----ABR4----P----Q----R
                !                      ! 
     Area 1     !         Area 0       !      Area 2     
     </artwork>
     </figure>
     <t>In this model, PCE has visibility into the topology (TED) of all 
     domains as well as the state of all active LSPs (LSP-DB) including 
     inter-domain LSPs. This model is thus well suited to take advantage 
     of all stateful PCE capabilities.</t>
     <t>It should be noted that in some deployments, a single stateful PCE may not be 
     possible because of administrative and confidentiality concerns.</t>
     </section>  
    
     <section title="Multiple Stateful PCE, Multiple Domains" toc="default">
     <t>In this model, there is at least one PCE per domain, 
     and each PCE has topology (TED) visibility restricted to its own domain.
     The inter-domain LSP state is synchronized to the ingress-PCE from 
     the ingress LSR (PCC), but this PCC may not be able to synchronize 
     to other PCEs
     (in transit or egress domains). This PCC may also choose to delegate 
     control over this LSP to the Ingress-PCE, which may issue 
     inter-domain path computation or re-optimization request to
     other PCEs. An inter-domain LSP that originates in a domain, is 
     synchronized to the PCE in that domain. A new procedure is needed
     to synchronize state of inter-domain LSP that do not originate in 
     the domain. In other words, inter-domain LSP state should also be
     synchronized to transit and egress PCEs as the inter-domain LSP 
     traverse through those domains.</t>
     <t>Following figure show an example of inter-AS case comprising
     of AS 100 and AS 200. A stateful PCE is deployed per AS.
     </t>
     <figure>
     <artwork align='center'>     
    ********                      ********
    * PCE1 *                      * PCE2 *
    ********                      ******** 
                
                !          !
                !          !  
A----B----C----ASBR1------ASBR2----D----E----F
|    |    |     |          |       |    |    |
|    |    |     |          |       |    |    |
G----H----I----ASBR3------ASBR4----J----K----L
                !          ! 
     AS100      !          !       AS200     
     </artwork>
     </figure>     
     <t>In order to conceal the information, a PCE may use path-key based 
     confidentiality mechanisms as per <xref target="RFC5520"/>.</t>
     <t>This section further describes considerations with respect to 
     each of the inter-domain path computation techniques.</t>
        <section title="Per Domain Path Computation" toc="default" anchor="SEC_PD">
    <t>The per domain path computation technique <xref target="RFC5152"/>
    is based on Multiple PCE Path Computation without Inter-PCE 
    Communication Model as described in <xref target="RFC4655"/>.
    It defines 
    a method where the path is computed during the signaling process (on a 
    per-domain basis). The entry Boundary Node (BN) of each domain is responsible 
    for performing the path computation for the section of the LSP that crosses 
    the domain, or for requesting that a PCE for that domain computes that piece 
    of the path.</t>
    <t>The ingress LSR would synchronize the state to the ingress 
    PCE, further the entry boundary nodes should also synchronize the state of 
    inter-domain LSP to transit and egress PCEs. Note that the BN on the 
    path of an LSP can probably see the path (through the Record 
    Route object in RSVP-TE signaling <xref target="RFC3209"/>) and 
    knows the bandwidth reserved for the LSP. Thus each
    entry BN along the path could be made responsible to synchronize 
    the LSP state to the transit/egress PCE(s).</t>
    <t>Since the stateful PCE(s) do not communicate during this 
    inter-domain path computation technique and each entry BN would perform
    path computation via Path Computation Request (PCReq) and Reply (PCRep) messages, 
	a passive
    stateful PCE is well suited for this case.</t>
    <t>In case of delegation to the ingress PCE (active stateful PCE), it would be capable of
    loose path computation only and make updates to the ingress LSR with
    this limited visibility. The entry BN would perform
    path computation via Path Computation Request and Reply messages (and thus rely on 
    the passive stateful mode). Thus the 
   inter-domain LSP is delegated only to the ingress PCE.</t>
    
        </section>  
        <section title="Backward-Recursive PCE-based Computation" toc="default" anchor="SEC_BRPC">
   <t>The BRPC <xref target="RFC5441"/> technique is based on 
   Multiple PCE Path Computation with Inter-PCE Communication Model 
   as described in <xref target="RFC4655"/>. It involves cooperation and 
   communication between PCEs in order to compute an optimal end-to-end path 
   across multiple domains. The sequence of domains to be traversed may be 
   known before the path computation, but it can also be used when the 
   domain path is unknown and determined during path computation.</t>
   <t>As described in <xref target="SEC_PD"/>, the entry boundary nodes 
   may synchronize the state of inter-domain LSPs to transit and egress 
   PCEs. An alternative approach may be for each PCE to synchronize the state 
   along the path across domains, i.e., each PCE would report the
   state to the next PCE(s) in the adjacent domain along the domain 
   sequence of the inter-domain path. A mechanism similar to state-sync
   described in <xref target='I-D.litkowski-pce-state-sync'/> may be 
   utilized for this purpose.</t> 
   <t>Some path segment in the end to end path may also be 
    hidden via path-key as per <xref target="RFC5520"/> during state 
	synchronization.</t>
   <t>In case of passive path computation request to the ingress PCE 
   from the ingress LSR the BRPC path computation procedure is applied 
   to compute end-to-end path by using PCReq and PCRep
   messages among stateful PCE(s) in passive mode. </t>
   <t>In case of delegation to the ingress PCE (active stateful PCE), the
   ingress PCE may trigger the end-to-end path computation via the same
   BRPC procedure using the path computation request and 
   reply messages among stateful PCE(s) (acting in passive mode). For 
   re-optimization the ingress PCE still rely on the same 
   BRPC procedure triggered by the ingress PCE. Ultimately the inter-domain LSP 
   is delegated to the ingress PCE and only the ingress PCE can 
   trigger end-to-end (E2E) path re-optimization with help of 
   transit/egress PCE using the BRPC procedure, based on the result 
   the ingress PCE would issue updates to the inter-domain LSP.
</t>
   <section title="Delegation" toc="default">
      <t>As noted in this document, the inter-domain LSP 
   is delegated to the ingress PCE and only the ingress PCE can issue updates to 
   the inter-domain LSP. The ingress PCE is responsible to trigger E2E path 
   re-optimization.</t>
   <t>Thus the ingress PCE can recommend updation for all aspects of the inter-domain LSP 
   including the segment of path in another domain (which it may have computed 
    with the help of other cooperating PCEs). These interaction between PCEs 
  for the inter-domain path computation are done using PCReq/PCRep messages 
  (i.e., in a passive mode).</t>
   <t>The transit/egress PCE cannot update any attribute of the inter-domain LSP
   on its own as it may not have any interaction with the ingress LSR. A mechanism 
   may be developed for transit/egress PCE to inform the ingress PCE
   to trigger E2E re-optimization and choose to update the inter-domain LSP based
   on the result. Also the ingress PCE may use combination of local information 
   and events along with some external mechanism (management / monitoring interface) 
   to trigger E2E path re-optimization.
</t>
    <t>Though ingress PCE can recommend update for path segments in other domains,
  the entry boundary node of that domain can apply policy control during signaling
  as explained in <xref target="RFC4105"/> and <xref target="RFC4216"/>. </t>
    </section>
    <section title="PCE-initiated LSP" toc="default">
  <t><xref target="RFC8281"/> describes setup, 
  maintenance and teardown of PCE-initiated LSPs under the stateful 
  PCE model, without the need for
   local configuration on the PCC. Similar to LSP updation, 
   the inter-domain LSP can be initiated by the ingress PCE using the 
   PCInitiate message to the ingress LSR. Note that per-domain LSP may 
   also be initiated by respective domain's PCE and stitched together.</t>
  </section>
    <section title="LSP Stitching" toc="default">
      <t><xref target="I-D.dugeon-pce-stateful-interdomain"/> describes 
a proposal to combine a Backward Recursive method with PCInitiate message to setup independent
   paths per domain, and combine these different paths together in order
   to operated them as end-to-end inter-domain paths without the need of
   signaling session between AS border routers.
    </t>
    </section>
        </section>  
        <section title="Hierarchical PCE" toc="default">
    <t>In H-PCE <xref target="RFC6805"/> architecture, the parent PCE is used to 
    compute a multi-domain path based on the domain connectivity information. 
    The parent PCE may be requested to provide a end-to-end path or only 
    the sequence of domains.</t>    
	
    <t>As described in <xref target="SEC_PD"/> and <xref target="SEC_BRPC"/>, the entry boundary nodes 
   may synchronize the state of inter-domain LSP to transit and egress 
   child PCEs. In this case, it might not be possible to synchronize state to the
   parent PCE. 
   If the parent PCE provides the sequence of domains and BRPC 
   procedure is used to get the E2E path, each PCE may be responsible to synchronize the state 
   along the path across domains similar to <xref target="SEC_BRPC"/>. 
   An alternative approach may be for ingress PCE to synchronize
   LSP state with the Parent PCE and it may further synchronize the state 
   to the child PCE(s) along the path across domains, i.e. parent PCE would report the
   state to the child PCE(s) along the domain 
   sequence.</t>
<t>Some path segment  in the end to end path may also be 
    hidden via path-key as per <xref target="RFC5520"/> during state synchronization.</t>
   <t>In case of passive path computation request to the ingress PCE 
   from the ingress LSR, the H-PCE path computation procedure is applied 
   to compute sequence of domains or end-to-end path by using PCReq and 
   PCRep messages among stateful PCE(s) in passive mode. </t>
   <t>In case of delegation to the ingress PCE (active stateful PCE), the
   ingress child PCE may further delegate to parent PCE as per <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-stateful-hpce'/>. The parent PCE 
   could update the path of the inter-domain LSP. Both per-domain stitched LSP as well as E2E contiguous LSP are possible. 
   Further parent PCE could also initiate the creation of LSP for both per-domain stitched LSP to all child PCE or E2E contiguous LSP to ingress child PCE as described in <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-stateful-hpce'/>.</t>    
        </section>  
     </section>  
    </section>  


    <section title="Security Considerations" toc="default">
      <t>The security considerations are as per <xref target="RFC5440"/> and 
	  <xref target="RFC8231"/>. Any multi-domain operation 
	  necessarily involves the exchange 
   of information across domain boundaries.  This may represent a 
   significant security and confidentiality risk especially when the 
   domains are controlled by different commercial entities.  PCEP 
   allows individual PCEs to maintain confidentiality of their domain 
   path information by using path-keys <xref target="RFC5520"/>.</t>


    </section>
    <section title="Manageability Considerations" toc="default">
      <section title="Control of Function and Policy" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new control of 
        function and policy requirements.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Information and Data Models" toc="default">
        <t><xref target='RFC7420'/> describes the PCEP MIB, there are no new MIB Objects 
        for this document.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Liveness Detection and Monitoring" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new liveness detection 
        and monitoring requirements in addition to those already listed in 
        <xref target="RFC5440"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Verify Correct Operations" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new operation 
        verification requirements in addition to those already listed in 
        <xref target="RFC5440"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Requirements On Other Protocols" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new requirements 
        on other protocols.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Impact On Network Operations" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not have any impact on 
        network operations in addition to those already listed in 
        <xref target="RFC5440"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>    
    <section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">
    <t>This is an informational document and has no IANA considerations.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Acknowledgments" toc="default">
      <t>The authors would like to that Young Lee, Haomian Zheng, Fatai Zhang for this comments.</t>
    </section>    
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5440.xml" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8231.xml"?>
    
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3209.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4105.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4216.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4655.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5152.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5441.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5520.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6805.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7420.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8051.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8281.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-pce-stateful-hpce"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.litkowski-pce-state-sync"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.dugeon-pce-stateful-interdomain"?>
      

    </references>
<section title="Contributor Addresses" toc="default">
    <t>
    <figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
          <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[
Udayasree Palle
Huawei Technologies
Divyasree Techno Park, Whitefield
Bangalore, Karnataka  560066
India

EMail: udayasreereddy@gmail.com

             
Avantika
Huawei Technologies
Divyasree Techno Park, Whitefield
Bangalore, Karnataka  560066
India

EMail: s.avantika.avantika@gmail.com


        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
    </section>    
  </back>
</rfc>
