<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="Yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-pce-stateful-pce-optional-09"
     ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" submissionType="IETF" updates="8231"
     xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="STATEFUL-OPT">Extension for Stateful PCE to allow Optional
    Processing of PCE Communication Protocol (PCEP) Objects</title>

    <author fullname="Cheng Li" initials="C." surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>c.l@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Haomian Zheng" initials="H." surname="Zheng">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>H1, Huawei Xiliu Beipo Village, Songshan Lake</street>

          <city>Dongguan</city>

          <region>Guangdong</region>

          <code>523808</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>zhenghaomian@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stephane Litkowski" initials="S" surname="Litkowski">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>slitkows.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>PCE Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document introduces a mechanism to mark some of the Path
      Computation Element (PCE) Communication Protocol (PCEP) objects as
      optional during PCEP messages exchange for the Stateful PCE model to
      allow relaxing some constraints during path computation and setup. This
      document introduces this relaxation to stateful PCE and updates RFC
      8231.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t><xref target="RFC5440"/> describes the Path Computation Element
      Communication Protocol (PCEP) which enables communication between a
      Path Computation Client (PCC) and a Path Control Element (PCE), or
      between two PCEs based on the PCE architecture <xref
      target="RFC4655"/>.</t>

      <t>PCEP Extensions for Stateful PCE Model <xref target="RFC8231"/>
      describes a set of extensions to PCEP to enable active control of
      Multiprotocol Label Switching Traffic Engineering (MPLS-TE) and
      Generalized MPLS (GMPLS) tunnels. <xref target="RFC8281"/> describes the
      setup and teardown of PCE-initiated LSPs under the active stateful PCE
      model, without the need for local configuration on the PCC, thus
      allowing for dynamic control.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC5440"/> defined the P flag (Processing-Rule) in the
      Common Object Header to allow a PCC to specify in a Path Computation
      Request (PCReq) message (sent to a PCE) whether the object must be taken
      into account by the PCE during path computation or is optional. The I
      flag (Ignore) is used by the PCE in a Path Computation Reply (PCRep)
      message to indicate to a PCC whether or not an optional object was
      considered by the PCE during path computation. Stateful PCE <xref
      target="RFC8231"/> specified that the P and I flags of the PCEP objects
      defined in <xref target="RFC8231"/> is to be set to zero on transmission
      and ignored on receipt, since they are exclusively related to the path
      computation requests. The behaviour for P and I flag in other messages
      defined in <xref target="RFC5440"/> and other extension was not
      specified. This document specifies how the P and I flag could be used in
      the stateful PCE model to identify optional objects in the Path
      Computation State Report (PCRpt) <xref target="RFC8231"/>, the Path
      Computation Update Request (PCUpd) <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and the LSP
      Initiate Request (PCInitiate) <xref target="RFC8281"/> message.</t>

      <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC8231"/> concerning usage
      of the P and I flag as well as the handling of unknown objects in the
      stateful PCEP message exchange.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language" toc="default">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
        14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
        when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

        <!--
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
        in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>-->
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview" toc="default">
      <t><xref target="RFC5440"/> describes the handling of unknown objects as
      per the setting of the P flag for the PCReq message. Further, <xref
      target="RFC8231"/> defined the usage of the LSP Error Code TLV in the
      PCRpt message in response to failed LSP Update Request via the PCUpd
      message (for example, due to an unsupported object/TLV).</t>

      <t>This document specifies the procedure of marking some objects as
      'optional to be processed' by the PCEP peer in the stateful PCEP
      messages. Furthermore, this document updates the procedure for handling
      unknown objects in the stateful PCEP messages based on the P flag.</t>

      <section title="Usage Example" toc="default">
        <t>The PCRpt message is used to report the current state of an LSP. As
        part of the message both the &lt;intended-attribute-list&gt; and
        &lt;actual-attribute-list&gt; is encoded (see <xref
        target="RFC8231"/>). For example, the &lt;intended-attribute-list&gt;
        could include the METRIC object to indicate a limiting constraint
        (Bound 'B' flag set) for the Path Delay Variation metric <xref
        target="RFC8233"/>. In some scenarios, it would be useful to state
        that this limiting constraint can be relaxed by the PCE in case it
        cannot find a path. <!--Similarly in the case of an association group
        <xref target="RFC8697"/> such as Disjoint Association <xref
        target="RFC8800"/>, the PCE may need to completely relax the
        disjointness constraint in order to provide a path to all the LSPs
        that are part of the association.--> In these cases it would be useful to
        mark the objects as 'optional' and it could be ignored by the PCEP
        peer. Also, it would be useful for the PCEP speaker to learn if the
        PCEP peer has relaxed the constraint and ignored the processing of the
        PCEP object.</t>

        <t>Thus, this document specifies how the already existing P
        and I flag in the PCEP common object header could be used during the
        stateful PCEP message exchange. Further, it should be noted that
        similar to handling of P and I flag in <xref target="RFC5440"/>, the
        flag applies to full PCEP Object and could not be applied to the
        granularity of an optional TLVs encoded in the PCEP Object.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="PCEP Extension" toc="default">
      <section title="STATEFUL-PCE-CAPABILITY TLV" toc="default">
        <t>A PCEP speaker indicates its ability to support the handling of the
        P and I flag in the stateful PCEP message exchange during the PCEP
        initialization phase, as follows. During the PCEP initialization phase,
        a PCC sends an Open message with an OPEN object that
        contains the STATEFUL-PCE-CAPABILITY TLV, as defined in <xref
        target="RFC8231"/>. A new flag, the R (RELAX) flag, is added to this
        TLV to indicate the support for relaxing the processing of some
        objects via the use of the P and I flag in the PCEP common object
        header.</t>

        <t>R (RELAX bit - TBD1): If set to 1 by a PCEP Speaker, the R flag
        indicates that the PCEP Speaker is willing to handle
        the P and I flags in the PCEP common object header for the PCEP objects in
        the stateful PCEP messages. In case the bit is unset, it indicates that
        the PCEP Speaker would not handle the P and I flags in the PCEP common
        object header for stateful PCE messages.</t>

        <t>The R flag MUST be set by both PCC and PCE to indicate support
        for the handling of the P and I flag in the PCEP common object header
        to allow relaxing some constraints by marking objects as 'optional to
        process'. If the PCEP speaker did not set the R flag but receives PCEP
        objects with P or I bit set, it MUST behave as per the processing rule
        in <xref target="RFC8231"/>. Note that while <xref target="RFC8231"/>
        stated that P and I flags of the PCEP objects defined in <xref target="RFC8231"/>
        are set to 0 on transmission and ignored on receipt, it did not say anything about already existing PCEP objects and thus the behaviour remained undefined. To safely use this future, both peers need to set the R flag.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Handling of P flag" toc="default">
        <section title="The PCRpt Message" toc="default">
          <t>The P flag in the PCRpt message <xref target="RFC8231"/> allows a
          PCC to specify to a PCE whether the object must be taken into
          account by the PCE (during state maintenance, path computation,
          or re-optimisation) or is optional to process. When the P flag is set
          in the PCRpt message received on a PCEP session on which the R bit was
          set by both peers, the object SHOULD be taken into account by the PCE.
          Conversely, when the P flag is cleared, the object is optional and
          the PCE is free to ignore it. The P flag for the mandatory objects
          such as the LSP and the ERO (Explicit Route Object) object (intended
          path) MUST be set in the PCRpt message. If a mandatory object is
          received with the P flag set incorrectly according to the rules
          stated above, the receiving peer MUST send a PCErr message with
          Error-Type=10 (Reception of an invalid object) and Error-value=1
          (reception of an object with P flag not set). On a PCEP session on
          which R bit was set by both peers, the PCC SHOULD set the P flag by
          default, unless a local configuration or local policy indicates that
          some constraints (corresponding PCEP objects) can be marked as
          optional and could be ignored by the PCE or the object itself conveys informational parameters that can be safely ignored.</t>
        <section title="Delegation" toc="default">
        <t>Delegation is an operation to grant a PCE temporary rights to
        modify a subset of parameters on one or more LSPs by a PCC as
        described in <xref target="RFC8051"/>. Note that for the delegated
        LSPs, the PCE can update and mark some objects as ignored even when
        the PCC had set the P flag during the delegation. Similarly, the PCE can
        update and mark some objects as a 'must to process' even when the PCC had
        not set the P flag during delegation.</t>

        <t>The PCC MUST acknowledge this by sending the PCRpt message with the
        P flag set as per the PCE expectation for the corresponding object. In
        case PCC cannot accept this, it would react as per the processing
        rules of unacceptable update in <xref target="RFC8231"/>.</t>
      </section>
        </section>

        <section title="The PCUpd Message and the PCInitiate Message"
                 toc="default">
          <t>The P flag in the PCUpd message <xref target="RFC8231"/> and the
          PCInitiate message <xref target="RFC8281"/> allows a PCE to specify
          to a PCC whether the object must be taken into account by the PCC
          (during path setup) or is optional to process. When the P flag is
          set in the PCUpd/PCInitiate message received on a PCEP session on
          which R bit was set by both peers, the object MUST be taken into
          account by the PCC. Conversely, when the P flag is cleared, the
          object is optional and the PCC is free to ignore it. The P flag for
          the mandatory objects such as the SRP (Stateful PCE Request
          Parameters), the LSP and the ERO MUST be set in the PCUpd/PCInitiate
          message. If a mandatory object is received with the P flag set
          incorrectly according to the rules stated above, the receiving peer
          MUST send a PCErr message with Error-Type=10 (Reception of an
          invalid object) and Error-value=1 (reception of an object with P
          flag not set). <!--By default, the PCE SHOULD set the P flag, unless a
          local configuration or local policy indicates that some constraints
          (corresponding PCEP objects) can be marked as optional and could be
          ignored by the PCC.-->
          On a PCEP session in which both peers set R bit, the
   PCE SHOULD set the P flag by default unless a local configuration/policy indicates that some constraints (corresponding PCEP
   objects) can be marked as optional and could be ignored by the PCC or the object itself conveys informational parameters that can be safely ignored.

          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Handling of I flag" toc="default">
        <section title="The PCUpd Message" toc="default">
          <t>The I flag in the PCUpd message <xref target="RFC8231"/> allows a
          PCE to indicate to a PCC whether or not an optional object was
          processed. The PCE MAY include the ignored optional object in its
          update request and set the I flag to indicate that the optional
          object was ignored. When the I flag is cleared, the PCE indicates
          that the optional object was processed.</t>

          <t>Note that when a PCE is unable to find the path that meets all
          the constraints as per the PCEP Object that cannot be ignored (i.e.
          the P flag is set), the PCUpd message MAY optionally include the PCEP
          Objects that caused the path computation to fail along with
          the empty ERO.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="The PCRpt Message" toc="default">
          <t>The I flag in the PCRpt message <xref target="RFC8231"/> allows a
          PCC to indicate to a PCE whether or not an optional object was
          processed in response to an LSP Update Request (PCUpd) or LSP
          Initiate Request (PCInitiate). The PCC MAY include the ignored
          optional object in its report and set the I flag to indicate that
          the optional object was ignored at PCC. When the I flag is cleared,
          the PCC indicates that the optional object was processed. The I flag
          has no meaning if the PCRpt message is not in response to a PCUpd or
          PCInitiate message (i.e. without the SRP object in the PCRpt
          message).</t>

          <t>Note that when a PCC is unable to set up the path that meets all
          the parameters as per the PCEP Object that cannot be ignored (i.e. the P
          flag is set), the PCRpt message MAY optionally include the PCEP
          Objects that caused the path setup to fail along with the
          LSP-ERROR-CODE TLV <xref target="RFC8231"/> indicating the reason
          for the failure.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="The PCInitiate Message" toc="default">
          <t>The I flag has no meaning in the PCinitiate message <xref
          target="RFC8281"/> and is ignored.</t>
        </section>
      </section>



      <section title="Unknown Object Handling" toc="default">
        <t>This document updates the handling of unknown objects in the
        stateful PCEP messages as per the setting of the P flag in the common
        object header in a similar way as <xref target="RFC5440"/>, i.e. if a
        PCEP speaker does not understand an object with the P flag set or
        understands the object but decides to ignore the object, the entire
        stateful PCEP message MUST be rejected and the PCE MUST send a PCErr
        message with Error-Type="Unknown Object" or "Not supported Object"
        <xref target="RFC5440"/>. In case the P flag is not set, the PCEP
        speaker is free to ignore the object and continue with the message
        processing as defined.</t>

        <t><xref target="RFC8231"/> defined LSP Error Code TLV to be carried
        in PCRpt message in the LSP object to convey error information. This
        document does not change that procedure.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" toc="default">
      <t>This document specifies how the already existing P and I flag in the PCEP
      common object header could be used during stateful PCEP exchanges. It
      updates the unknown object error handling in stateful PCEP message
      exchange. These changes on their own do not add any new security
      concerns. The security considerations identified in <xref
      target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref
      target="RFC8281"/> continue to apply.</t>

      <t>As per <xref target="RFC8231"/>, it is RECOMMENDED that these PCEP
      extensions can only be activated on authenticated and encrypted sessions
      across PCEs and PCCs belonging to the same administrative authority,
      using Transport Layer Security (TLS) <xref target="RFC8253"/> as per the
      recommendations and best current practices in <xref target="RFC9325"/>
      (unless explicitly set aside in <xref target="RFC8253"/>).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">
      <section title="STATEFUL-PCE-CAPABILITY TLV" toc="default">
        <t/>

        <t><xref target="RFC8231"/> defined the STATEFUL-PCE-CAPABILITY TLV and IANA created the "STATEFUL-PCE-CAPABILITY TLV Flag Field"
        subregistry to manage the value of the STATEFUL-PCE-CAPABILITY TLV's
        Flag field. IANA is requested to allocate a new bit in the
        subregistry, as follows:</t>

        <t><figure align="left" alt="" height="" suppress-title="false"
            title="" width="">
            <artwork align="left" alt="" height="" name="" type="" width=""
                     xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
Bit       Description                 Reference
-------------------------------------------------
TBD1      RELAX bit                   [This-I.D.]
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Imp" title="Implementation Status">
      <t>[Note to the RFC Editor - remove this section before publication, as
      well as remove the reference to RFC 7942.]</t>

      <t>This section records the status of known implementations of the
      protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of this
      Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in <xref
      target="RFC7942"/>. The description of implementations in this section
      is intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in progressing
      drafts to RFCs. Please note that the listing of any individual
      implementation here does not imply endorsement by the IETF. Furthermore,
      no effort has been spent to verify the information presented here that
      was supplied by IETF contributors. This is not intended as, and must not
      be construed to be, a catalog of available implementations or their
      features. Readers are advised to note that other implementations may
      exist.</t>

      <t>According to <xref target="RFC7942"/>, "this will allow reviewers and
      working groups to assign due consideration to documents that have the
      benefit of running code, which may serve as evidence of valuable
      experimentation and feedback that have made the implemented protocols
      more mature. It is up to the individual working groups to use this
      information as they see fit".</t>

      <t>At the time of posting the -09 version of this document, there are no
      known implementations of this mechanism. It is believed that some
      vendors are considering implementations, but these plans are too vague
      to make any further assertions.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Manageability Considerations" toc="default">
      <section title="Control of Function and Policy" toc="default">
        <t>An implementation supporting this document SHOULD allow configuration
        of the capability to support
        relaxation of constraints in the stateful PCEP message exchange. They
        SHOULD also allow configuration of related LSP constraints (or
        parameters) that are optional to process.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Information and Data Models" toc="default">
        <t>An implementation supporting this document SHOULD allow the
        operator to view the capability
        defined in this document. To serve this purpose, the PCEP YANG module
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang"/> could be extended in the
        future.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Liveness Detection and Monitoring" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new liveness
        detection and monitoring requirements in addition to those already
        listed in <xref target="RFC5440"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Verify Correct Operations" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new operation
        verification requirements in addition to those already listed in <xref
        target="RFC5440"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements On Other Protocols" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new
        requirements on other protocols.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Impact On Network Operations" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not have any impact on
        network operations in addition to those already listed in <xref
        target="RFC5440"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments" toc="default">
      <t>Thanks to Jonathan Hardwick for the discussion and suggestions around
      this draft.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Oscar Gonzalez de Dios, Mike Koldychev, Samuel Sidor,  and Peng Shaofu for the review comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5440.xml" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174.xml" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8231.xml" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8253.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8281.xml"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4655.xml" ?>



      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7942.xml" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8051.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8233.xml"?>





      <!--><?rfc include="reference.RFC.8697.xml"?>-->

      <!--><?rfc include="reference.RFC.8800.xml"?>-->

       <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9325.xml" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang"?>
    </references>

    <section title="Contributors" toc="default">
      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
Dhruv Dhody
Huawei
India

Email: dhruv.ietf@gmail.com
    ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
