<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="Yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-li-pce-controlled-id-space-07"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PCE Controlled ID Space">PCE Controlled ID Space</title>

    <author fullname="Cheng Li" initials="C." surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>c.l@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mach(Guoyi) Chen" initials="M." surname="Chen">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>Mach.chen@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Aijun Wang" initials="A." surname="Wang">
      <organization>China Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Beiqijia Town,</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region>Changping District</region>

          <code>102209</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>wangaj3@chinatelecom.cn</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Weiqiang Cheng" initials="W." surname="Cheng">
      <organization>China Mobile</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>chengweiqiang@chinamobile.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Chao Zhou" initials="C." surname="Zhou">
      <organization>HPE</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city></city>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>chaozhou_us@yahoo.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="30" month="October" year="2020"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) provides
      a mechanisms for the Path Computation Elements (PCEs) to perform path
      computation in response to a Path Computation Clients (PCCs) requests.
      The Stateful PCE extensions allow stateful control of Multiprotocol
      Label Switching (MPLS) Traffic Engineering (TE) Label Switched Paths
      (LSPs) using PCEP. Furthermore, PCE can be used for computing paths in
      the SR networks.</t>

      <t>Stateful PCE provide active control of MPLS-TE LSPs via PCEP, for a
      model where the PCC delegates control over one or more locally
      configured LSPs to the PCE. Further, stateful PCE could also create and
      remove PCE-initiated LSPs by itself. A PCE-based Central Controller (PCECC)
      simplify the processing of a distributed control plane by integrating
      with elements of Software-Defined Networking (SDN).</t>

      <t>In some use cases, such as PCECC or Binding Segment Identifier (SID)
      for Segment Routing (SR), there are requirements for a stateful PCE to
      make allocation of labels, SIDs, etc. These use cases require PCE aware
      of various identifier spaces from where to make allocations on behalf of a PCC.
      This document describes a mechanism for a PCC to inform the PCE of the
      identifier space set aside for the PCE control via PCEP. The identifier could be
      an MPLS label, a SID or any other to-be-defined identifier that can be allocated by
      a PCE.</t>

      <!--may need to dynamically allocate new labels or Segment IDs
      that come from a PCC's label space. However, in the existing documents,
      the label range to be used by a PCE is assumed to to be known and set on
      both PCEP peers, so the mechanism of label range delegation is required.
      This document describes a mechanism to advertise specific PCE controlled
      ID spaces to PCEs via PCEP channel. The type of ID can be MPLS label,
      SRv6 Path Segment or other ID.</t>-->
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="RFC5440"/> defines the stateless Path Computation
      Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) for thePath Computation Elements
      (PCEs) to perform path computation in response to a Path Computation
      Clients (PCCs) requests. For supporting stateful operations, <xref
      target="RFC8231"/> specifies a set of extensions to PCEP to enable
      stateful control of LSPs within and across PCEP sessions in compliance
      with <xref target="RFC4657"/>. Furthermore, <xref target="RFC8281"/>
      describes the setup, maintenance, and teardown of PCE-initiated LSPs
      under the stateful PCE model, without the need for local configuration
      on the PCC, thus allowing for a dynamic network that is centrally
      controlled and deployed.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC8283"/> introduces the architecture for PCE as a
      central controller, it examines the motivations and applicability for
      PCEP as a control protocol in this environment, and introduces the
      implications for the protocol. Also, <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller"/> specifies the
      procedures and PCEP extensions for using the PCE as a Central
      Controller (PCECC), where LSPs are calculated/set up/initiated and label
      forwarding entries are downloaded through extending PCEP. However, the
      document assumes that label range to be used by a PCE is known and set
      on both PCEP peers. This extension adds the capability to advertise the
      label range via a PCEP extension.</t>

      <!--these documents do not describe the mechanisms for PCEs to
      manage the space of MPLS label and allocate MPLS label for each of the
      routers that it controls. The label range to be used by a PCE is assumed
      to be known and set on both PCEP peers <xref
      target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller"/>.</t>-->

      <t>Similarly, <xref
      target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/> specifies the
      procedures and PCEP extensions when a PCE-based controller is
      also responsible for configuring the forwarding actions on the routers
      (SR SID distribution in this case), in addition to computing the paths
      for packet flows in a segment routing network and telling the edge
      routers what instructions to attach to packets as they enter the
      network. However, the document assumes that label range to be used by a
      PCE is known and set on both PCEP peers. This extension adds the
      capability to advertise the range (from SRGB or SRLB of the node) via a
      PCEP extension.</t>

      <t>In addition, <xref
      target="I-D.dhody-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-srv6"/> specifies
      the procedures and PCEP extensions of PCECC for SRv6. An SRv6
      SID is represented as LOC:FUNCT (<xref
          target="I-D.ietf-spring-srv6-network-programming"/>) where LOC is the L most significant bits
      and FUNCT is the 128-L least significant bits. The FUNCT part of the SID
      is an opaque identification of a local function bound to the SID. This
      extension adds the capability to advertise the range of Function ID
      (FUNCT part) via a PCEP extension.</t>

      <!--<t>PCE can influence/edit the SR path/MPLS LSP by allocating ID from PCE
      controlled ID space. The PCE controlled ID space MAY NOT be used for the
      VPN inner prefix(which can be done via traditional BGP protocol). Also,
      these controlled ID spaces SHOULD NOT be overlapped with other ID spaces
      that allocated by distributed protocols, such as label space that used
      for VPN allocated by BGP.</t>-->

      <t>Once the PCC/node has given control over an ID space (for example
      labels), the PCC/node MUST NOT allocate the ID from this ID space. For
      example, a PCC/node MUST NOT use this labels from the PCE controlled
      label space to make allocation for VPN Prefix distributed via BGP or
      labels used for LDP/RSVP-TE signalling. This is done to make sure that
      the PCE control over ID space does not conflict with the existing node
      allocation.</t>

      <t>The use case are described in <xref target="use"/>. The ID space
      range information can be advertised via the TLVs in the Open message.
      The detailed procedures are described in <xref target="pro"/>, and the
      objects' format is specified in <xref target="obj"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This memo makes use of the terms defined in <xref target="RFC5440"/>,
      <xref target="RFC8231"/>, <xref target="RFC8283"/> and <xref
      target="RFC8402"/>.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
        14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
        when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="use" title="Use cases">
      <section title="PCE-based Central Control">
        <t>A PCE-based Central Controller (PCECC) can simplify the processing
        of a distributed control plane by integrating with elements of SDN.
        Thus, the LSP/SR path can be calculated/set up/initiated and the
        label/SID forwarding entries can also be downloaded through a
        centralized PCE server to each network devices along the path while
        leveraging the existing PCE technologies as much as possible.</t>

        <section title="PCECC for MPLS/SR-MPLS">
          <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller"/>
          describes a mode where LSPs are provisioned as explicit label
          instructions at each hop on the end-to-end path. Each router along
          the path must be told what label forwarding instructions to program
          and what resources to reserve. The controller uses PCEP to
          communicate with each router along the path of the end-to-end LSP.
          For this to work, the PCE-based controller will take responsibility
          for managing some part of the MPLS label space for each router that
          it controls as described in section 3.1.2. of <xref
          target="RFC8283"/>. A mechanism for a PCC to inform the PCE of such
          a label space to control is needed within PCEP.</t>

          <t><xref target="RFC8664"/> specifies
          extensions to PCEP that allow a stateful PCE to compute, update or
          initiate SR-TE paths. <xref
          target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/> describes
          the mechanism for PCECC to allocate and provision the
          node/prefix/adjacency label (SID) via PCEP. To make such allocation,
          PCE needs to be aware of the label space from Segment Routing Global
          Block (SRGB) or Segment Routing Local Block (SRLB) <xref
          target="RFC8402"/> of the node that it can control. A mechanism for a
          PCC to inform the PCE of such label space to control is needed
          within PCEP. The full SRGB/SRLB of a node could be learned via
          existing IGP or BGP-LS mechanism.</t>

          <t/>
        </section>

        <section title="PCECC for SRv6">
          <t><xref target="I-D.dhody-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-srv6"/>
          describes the mechanism for PCECC to allocate and provision the SRv6
          SID via PCEP. An SRv6 SID is represented as LOC:FUNCT (<xref
          target="I-D.ietf-spring-srv6-network-programming"/>) where LOC is
          the L most significant bits and FUNCT is the 128-L least significant
          bits. The FUNCT part of the SID is an opaque identification of a
          local function bound to the SID. To make such allocation, PCE needs
          to be aware of the Function ID space (FUNCT part) of the node that
          it controls. A mechanism for a PCC to inform the PCE of such a
          Function ID space to control is needed within PCEP.</t>

          <t/>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Binding SID Allocation">
        <t>The headend of an SR Policy binds a Binding SID to its policy <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing-policy"/>. The instantiation
        of which may involve a list of SIDs. Currently Binding SID are
        allocated by the node <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-binding-label-sid"/>, but there is an inherent advantage in the
        Binding SID to be allocated by a PCE to allow SR policies to be
        dynamically created, updated according to the network status and
        operations. This is described in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller"/>. Therefore,
        a PCE needs to obtain the authority and control to allocate Binding
        SID actively from the PCC's label space as described in above use
        case.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="pro" title="Overview">
      <t>During PCEP Initialization Phase, Open messages are exchanged between
      the PCCs and the PCEs. The OPEN object may also contain a set of TLVs used to
      convey the capabilities in the Open message. The term 'ID' in this document,
      could be a MPLS label, SRv6 Function ID or any other future ID space for
      PCE to control and allocate from. A PCC can include a corresponding
      ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLVs in the OPEN Object to inform the corresponding ID
      space information that it wants the PCE to control. This TLV MUST NOT be
      included by the PCE and MUST be ignored on receipt by a PCC. This is an
      optional TLV, the PCE could be aware of the ID space from some other
      means outside of PCEP.</t>

      <t>For delegating multiple types of ID space, multiple TLVs
      corresponding to each ID type MUST be included in an Open message. The
      ID type can be MPLS label or other type of ID. The following
      ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLV is defined in this document - <list style="symbols">
          <t>LABEL-CONTROL-SPACE TLV - for MPLS Labels (including for
          SR-MPLS)</t>

          <t>FUNCTION-ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLV - for SRv6 SID Function ID</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The procedure of ID space control to PCE is shown below:</t>

      <t><figure anchor="fig1" title="ID space control to PCE">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 +-+-+                                     +-+-+
 |PCC|                                     |PCE|
 +-+-+                                     +-+-+
   |                                         |
   |   Open msg (LABEL-CONTROL-SPACE,etc)    |
   |                                         | 
   |--------                                 |
   |        \                     Open msg   |
   |         \  -----------------------------|
   |          \/                             |
   |          /\                             |
   |         /  ---------------------------->|
   |        /                                |
   |<------                       Keepalive  |
   |             ----------------------------|
   |Keepalive   /                            |
   |--------   /                             |
   |        \/                               |
   |        /\                               |
   |<------   ------------------------------>|
   |                                         |

]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>If the ID space control procedure is successful, the PCE will return
      a KeepAlive message to the PCC. If there is any error in processing the
      corresponding TLV, an Error (PCErr) message will be sent to the PCC with
      Error-Type=1 (PCEP session establishment failure) and Error-value=TBD
      (ID space control failure).</t>

      <t>After this process, a stateful PCE can learn the PCE-controlled ID
      spaces of a node (PCC) under its control. A PCE can then allocate IDs
      within the controlled-ID space. For example, a PCE can actively allocate
      labels and download forwarding instructions for the PCECC LSP as
      described in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller"/>. A PCE can
      also allocate labels from the PCE controlled portion of the SRGB/SRLB
      for PCECC-SR <xref
      target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/>. The full
      SRGB/SRLB of a node could be learned via existing IGP or BGP-LS
      mechanism.</t>
      <t>The procedure for handling the FUNCTION-ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLV is same as above.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="obj" title="Objects">
      <t/>

      <section title="Open Object">
        <t>For advertising the PCE-controlled ID space to a PCE, this document
        defines several TLVs within the OPEN object.</t>

        <section title="LABEL-CONTROL-SPACE TLV">
          <t>For a PCC to inform the label space under the PCE control, this
          document defines a new LABEL-CONTROL-SPACE TLV.</t>

          <t>The LABEL-CONTROL-SPACE TLV is an optional TLV in the OPEN
          object, and its format is shown in the following figure:</t>

          <t><figure anchor="fig2" title="LABEL-CONTROL-SPACE TLV">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Type=TBD1          |            Length             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Block        |                   Flags                       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                    Start (1)                  |   Reserved    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                    Range (1)                  |   Reserved    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                              ...                              |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                              ...                              |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                    Start (n)                  |   Reserved    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                    Range (n)                  |   Reserved    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The type (16 bits) of the TLV is TBD1. The length field (16 bits)
          and has a variable value.</t>

          <t>Block(8 bits): the number of ID blocks. The range of a block is
          described by a start field and a range field.</t>

          <t>Flags (24 bits): No flag is currently defined. The unassigned
          bits of Flags field MUST be set to 0 on transmission and MUST be
          ignored on receipt.</t>

          <t>Start(i) (24 bits): indicates the beginning of the label block
          i.</t>

          <t>Range(i) (24 bits): indicates the range of the label block i.</t>

          <t>Reserved: MUST be set to 0 on transmission and MUST be ignored
          on reception.</t>

          <t>LABEL-CONTROL-SPACE TLV SHOULD be included only once in a Open
          Message. On receipt, only the first instance is processed and others
          MUST be ignored.</t>

          <t>A stateful PCE can actively allocate labels and download
          forwarding instructions for the PCECC LSP as described in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller"/>. A PCE can
          also allocate labels from SRGB/SRLB for PCECC-SR <xref
          target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr"/>. The
          Binding Segments can also be selected for the PCE controlled space
          <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller"/>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="FUNCT-ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLV">
          <t>For a PCC to inform the SRv6 SID Function ID space under the PCE
          control, this document defines a new FUNCT-ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLV.</t>

          <t>The FUNCT-ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLV is an optional TLV for use in the
          OPEN object, and its format is shown in the following figure:</t>

          <t><figure anchor="fig3" title="FUNCT-ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLV">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Type=TBD2          |            Length             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Block      |             Flags                           |L|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                            Start (1)                          |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                            Range (1)                          |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                             ......                            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                            Start (n)                          |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                            Range (n)                          |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Loc Size     | Locator (variable)...                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
            </figure>The type (16 bits) of the TLV is TBD2. The length field
          (16 bits) and has a variable value.</t>

          <t>Block(8 bits): the number of ID blocks. The range of a block is
          described by a start field and a range field.</t>

          <t>Flags (24 bits): Following flags are currently defined</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>L-flag: Locator flag, set when the locator information is
              included in this TLV. If L-flag is unset, Loc Size and variable
              Locator field MUST NOT be included in this TLV, and the ID
              spaces are applicable to all Locators.</t>
            </list>The unassigned bits of Flags field MUST be set to 0 on
          transmission and MUST be ignored on receipt.</t>

          <t>Start(i) (128 bits): indicates the beginning of the Function ID
          block i.</t>

          <t>Range(i) (128 bits): indicates the range of the Function ID block
          i.</t>

          <t>Loc size(8 bits): indicates the bit length of a Locator. Appears
          only when the L-flag is set.</t>

          <t>Locator (variable length): the value of a Locator. The Function
          ID spaces specified in this TLV are associated with this
          locator.</t>

          <t>As per <xref target="RFC5440"/>, the value portion of the PCEP
          TLV needs to be 4-bytes aligned, so a FUNCT-ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLV is
          padded with trailing zeros to a 4-byte boundary.</t>

          <t>Multiple FUNCT-ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLVs MAY be included in a OPEN
          object to specify Function ID space specefic to each locator.</t>

          <t>A stateful PCE can actively allocate SRv6 SID and download
          SIDs for the PCECC-SRv6 as described in
          <xref
          target="I-D.dhody-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-srv6"/>.</t>

          <t>Note that SRv6 SID allocation involves LOC:FUNCT; the LOC is
          assumed to be known at PCE and FUNCT is allocated from the PCE
          controlled Function ID block.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="other" title="Other Considerations">
      <t>In case of multiple PCEs, a PCC MAY decide to give control over
      different ID space to each instance of the PCE. In case a PCC includes
      the same ID space to multiple PCEs, the PCE MUST use synchronization
      mechanism (such as <xref target="I-D.litkowski-pce-state-sync"/>) to
      avoid allocating the same ID.</t>

      <t>The PCE would allocate ID from the PCE controlled ID space. The PCC
      would not allocate ID by itself from this space as long as it has an
      active PCEP session to a PCE to which it has given control over the ID
      space.</t>

      <t>Note that if there is any change in the ID space, the PCC MUST bring
      the session down and re-establish the session with new TLVs. During
      state synchronization the PCE would need to consider the new ID space
      into consideration and SHOULD re-establish the LSP/SR-paths if
      needed.</t>

      <t>The PCC can regain control of the ID space by closing the PCEP
      session and require new session without ID space TLVs specified in this
      document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA maintains the "Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers" registry.
    This document requests IANA actions to allocate code points for the protocol elements
    defined in this document.</t>
    <section title="PCEP TLV Type Indicators">

   <t>IANA maintains a subregistry called "PCEP TLV Type Indicators".  IANA is requested to
      make an assignment from this subregistry as follows:</t>

   <figure>
     <artwork>
       <![CDATA[
Value   | Meaning                      | Reference
--------+------------------------------+-------------
 TBD1   | LABEL-CONTROL-SPACE TLV      | [This.I-D]
 TBD2   | FUNCT-ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLV   | [This.I-D]
       ]]>
     </artwork>
   </figure>
 </section>

<section title="LABEL-CONTROL-SPACE TLV's Flag field" toc="default">
        <t>This document defines the
      LABEL-CONTROL-SPACE TLV and requests that IANA to create a new sub-registry to
      manage the value of the LABEL-CONTROL-SPACE TLV's 24-bits Flag field.   New
   values are to be assigned by Standards Action <xref target="RFC8126"/>.  Each bit
   should be tracked with the following qualities:<list style="symbols">

   <t>Bit number (counting from bit 0 as the most significant bit)</t>

   <t>Capability description</t>

   <t>Defining RFC</t></list></t>
   <t>Currently, there is no allocation in this registry.</t>
   
   <figure>
     <artwork>
       <![CDATA[
 Bit    | Name                         | Reference
--------+------------------------------+-------------
 0-23   | Unassigned                   | [This.I-D]
       ]]>
     </artwork>
   </figure>
      </section>
<section title="FUNCT-ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLV's Flag field" toc="default">
        <t>This document defines the
      FUNCT-ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLV and requests that IANA to create a new sub-registry to
      manage the value of the FUNCT-ID-CONTROL-SPACE TLV's 24-bits Flag field.   New
   values are to be assigned by Standards Action <xref target="RFC8126"/>.  Each bit
   should be tracked with the following qualities:<list style="symbols">

   <t>Bit number (counting from bit 0 as the most significant bit)</t>

   <t>Capability description</t>

   <t>Defining RFC</t></list></t>
   <t>Currently, there is no allocation in this registry.</t>
   
   <figure>
     <artwork>
       <![CDATA[
 Bit    | Name                         | Reference
--------+------------------------------+-------------
 23     | L-Bit                        | [This.I-D] 
 0-22   | Unassigned                   | [This.I-D]
       ]]>
     </artwork>
   </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations"
             toc="default">
    <t>The security considerations described in 
     <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller'/>, <xref target='I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr'/>, and <xref target='I-D.dhody-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-srv6'/> and apply to the
     extensions described in this document.</t>

      <t>As per <xref target="RFC8231"/>, it is RECOMMENDED that these PCEP extensions only be activated on authenticated and encrypted sessions across PCEs and PCCs belonging to the same administrative authority, using Transport Layer Security (TLS) <xref target="RFC8253"/> as per the recommendations and best current practices in <xref target="RFC7525"/> (unless explicitly set aside in <xref target="RFC8253"/>).</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TBD.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5440'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8126'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8231'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8281"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8253'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8283'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4657'?>

      <!--<?rfc include='reference.I-D.li-pce-sr-path-segment'?>-->
      
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7525'?>
      
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8402'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8664'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-sr'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.litkowski-pce-state-sync'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing-policy'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.dhody-pce-pcep-extension-pce-controller-srv6'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-spring-srv6-network-programming'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-binding-label-sid'?>
    </references>

    <section title="Contributors">
      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[   Dhruv Dhody
   Huawei Technologies
   Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield
   Bangalore, Karnataka 560066
   India

   EMail: dhruv.ietf@gmail.com


   Zhenbin Li
   Huawei Technologies
   Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.
   Beijing 100095
   China

   EMail: lizhenbin@huawei.com


   Jie Dong
   Huawei Technologies
   Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.
   Beijing 100095
   China

   EMail: jie.dong@huawei.com

]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t/>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
