<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc strict="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-pce-stateful-path-protection-00" ipr="trust200902">
    <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
    <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
    <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
    <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
    <?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
    <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
    <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Stateful PCE LSP Path Protection">PCEP Extensions for MPSL-TE LSP Path Protection with stateful PCE</title>
    <author fullname="Hariharan Ananthakrishnan" initials="H." surname="Ananthakrishnan">
      <organization>Packet Design</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
            <street>1 South Almaden Blvd, #1150,</street>
          <city>San Jose, CA, 95113</city>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>hari@packetdesign.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Siva Sivabalan" initials="S."  surname="Sivabalan">
        <organization>Cisco</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>2000 Innovation Drive</street>
                <city>Kananta, Ontaria K2K 3E8</city>
                <country>Canada</country>
            </postal>
            <email>msiva@cisco.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Colby Barth" initials="C."  surname="Barth">
        <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>1194 N Mathilda Ave,</street>
                <city>Sunnyvale, CA, 94086</city>
                <country>USA</country>
            </postal>
            <email>cbarth@juniper.net</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Raveendra Torvi" initials="R."   surname="Torvi">
        <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>1194 N Mathilda Ave,</street>
                <city>Sunnyvale, CA, 94086</city>
                <country>USA</country>
            </postal>
            <email>rtorvi@juniper.net</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Ina Minei" initials="I." surname="Minei">
        <organization>Google, Inc</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
                <city>Mountain View, CA, 94043</city>
                <country>USA</country>
            </postal>
            <email>inaminei@google.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Edward Crabbe" initials="E." surname="Crabbe">
        <organization>Individual Contributor</organization>
        <address>
            <email>edward.crabbe@gmail.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D" surname="Dhody" fullname="Dhruv Dhody">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560066</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>dhruv.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>    
    <!-- month and day will be generated automatically by XML2RFC;
be sure the year is current.-->

    <date  year="2018" /> <!--04 as uploaded-->

    <workgroup>PCE Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>PCEP</keyword>

<abstract>
<t> A stateful Path Computation Element (PCE) is capable of computing as well as controlling via 
Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) Multiprotocol Label Switching Traffic Engineering Label Switched Paths (MPLS LSP).  
Furthermore, it is also possible for a stateful PCE to create, maintain, and delete LSPs. This document describes 
PCEP extension to associate two or more LSPs to provide end-to-end path protection.</t>
</abstract>
 
</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t> <xref target="RFC5440"/> describes PCEP for communication between a Path Computation Client (PCC) and a PCE or 
between one a pair of PCEs as per <xref target="RFC4655"/>.  A PCE computes paths for MPLS-TE LSPs based on various constraints and optimization criteria. </t>

 <t> Stateful pce <xref target="RFC8231"/> specifies a set of extensions to PCEP to enable 
stateful control of paths such as MPLS TE LSPs between and across PCEP sessions in compliance with <xref target="RFC4657"/>. 
It includes mechanisms to effect LSP state synchronization between PCCs and PCEs, delegation of control of LSPs 
to PCEs, and PCE control of timing and sequence of path computations within and across PCEP sessions and focuses 
on a model where LSPs are configured on the PCC and control over them is delegated to the PCE. Furthermore, a 
mechanism to dynamically instantiate LSPs on a PCC based on the requests from a stateful PCE or a controller 
using stateful PCE, is specified in <xref target="RFC8281"/>.</t>

<t>Path protection <xref target="RFC4427"/> refers to a paradigm in which the working LSP is protected by one or more protection LSP(s). 
When the working LSP fails, protection LSP(s) is/are activated. When the working LSPs are computed and controlled 
by the PCE, there is benefit in a mode of operation where protection LSPs are as well. </t>

<t>This document specifies a stateful PCEP extension to associate two or more LSPs for the purpose of setting up 
path protection. The proposed extension covers the following scenarios:
    <list style="symbols">
    <t>A PCC initiates a protection LSP and retains the control of the LSP. The PCC computes the path itself or makes a 
        request for path computation to a PCE. After the path setup, it reports the information and state of the path to the PCE. 
        This includes the association group identifying the working and protection LSPs.
        This is the passive stateful mode <xref target="RFC8051"/>.
    </t>
    <t>A PCC initiates a protection LSP and delegates the control of the LSP to a stateful PCE. During delegation the association group identifying the working and protection LSPs is included. The PCE 
    computes the path for the protection LSP and update the PCC with the information about the path as long as it controls the LSP. 
    This is the active stateful mode <xref target="RFC8051"/>.
    </t>

    <t>A protection LSP could be initiated by a stateful PCE, which retains the control of the LSP. 
    The PCE is responsible for computing the path of the LSP and updating to the PCC with the information about the path. 
    This is the PCE Initiated mode <xref target="RFC8281"/>.
    </t> 
    
    
      </list>

Note that protection LSP can be established (signaled) prior to the failure (in which case the LSP is said to be in standby mode <xref target="RFC4427"/>) or post failure of the corresponding working LSP according to the operator choice/policy.

</t>
<t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> introduces a generic mechanism to
   create a grouping of LSPs which can then be used to define
   associations between a set of LSPs that is equally applicable to
   stateful PCE (active and passive modes) and stateless PCE.</t>

   <t>This document specifies a PCEP extension to associate one working LSP with one or more
   protection LSPs using the generic association mechanism.</t>

   <t>This document describes a PCEP
   extension to associate protection LSPs by creating Path Protection Association Group (PPAG)
   and encoding this association in PCEP messages for stateful PCEP
   sessions.
   </t>
    <section title="Requirements Language" toc="default">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they
      appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
</section> <!-- Introduction --> 

<section title="Terminology">

<t>The following terminologies are used in this document:
      <list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="ERO:"> Explicit Route Object.</t>
        <t hangText="LSP:"> Label Switched Path.</t>
        <t hangText="PCC:"> Path Computation Client.</t>
        <t hangText="PCE:"> Path Computation Element</t>
        <t hangText="PCEP:"> Path Computation Element Protocol.</t>
        <t hangText="PPAG:"> Path Protection Association Group.</t>
        <t hangText="TLV:"> Type, Length, and Value.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
</section> <!-- Terminology --> 
    
<section anchor="Extension-Overview" title="PCEP Extensions">

<section anchor="Path-Protection-Association-Type" title="Path Protection Association Type">

<t>LSPs are not associated by listing the other LSPs with which they interact, but rather by making them 
belong to an association group referred to as "Path Protection Association Group" (PPAG) in this document. 
All LSPs join a PPAG individually. PPAG is based on the generic Association object used to associate two 
or more LSPs specified in <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref>. A member of a PPAG can 
take the role of working or protection LSP. This document defines a new association type called 
"Path Protection Association Type" of value TBD1. A PPAG can have one working LSP and/or one or more
protection LSPs. The source, destination and Tunnel ID (as carried in LSP-IDENTIFIERS TLV <xref target="RFC8231"/>, with description as per <xref target="RFC3209"/>) of all LSPs within a PPAG MUST be the same. As per <xref target="RFC3209"/>, TE tunnel is used to associate a set of LSPs during reroute or to spread a traffic trunk over multiple paths.</t>

<t>The format of the Association object used for PPAG is specified in 
<xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref>.</t>


<!--<figure anchor="PPAG-IPv4-Association-Object-Fmt" title="PPAG IPv4 ASSOCIATION Object format">
<artwork><![CDATA[

   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |         Reserved            |              Flags            |R|
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  Association type = TBD1    |          Association            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                IPv4 Association Source                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   //            Optional TLVs                                    //
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
       
<figure anchor="PPAG-IPv6-Association-Object-Fmt" title="PPAG IPv6 ASSOCIATION Object format">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |         Reserved            |              Flags            |R|
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  | Association Type = TBD1     |          Association            |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                                                               |
  |                IPv6 Association Source                        |
  |                                                               |
  |                                                               |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  //            Optional TLVs                                    //
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
-->    

       <t>This document defines a new Association type, the Path Protection Association type, 
       value will be assigned by IANA (TBD1).
       </t> 
   
   <t>This Association-Type is dynamic in nature and created by the PCC or PCE for
   the LSPs belonging to the same TE tunnel (as described in <xref target="RFC3209"/>) originating at the same head node and terminating at the same destination. 
   These associations are
   conveyed via PCEP messages to the PCEP peer.  Operator-configured
   Association Range MUST NOT be set for this association-type and
   MUST be ignored.</t>

</section> 

<section anchor="Path-Protection-Association-TLV" title="Path Protection Association TLV">
<t>The Path Protection Association TLV is an optional TLV for use with the Path Protection
Association Object Type. The Path Protection Association TLV MUST NOT be present more than once. 
If it appears more than once,
only the first occurrence is processed and any others MUST be ignored. </t>

<t> The Path Protection Association TLV follows the PCEP TLV format of <xref target="RFC5440" />. </t> 

<t> The type (16 bits) of the TLV is to be assigned by IANA. The length 
field is 16 bit-long and has a fixed value of 4.</t> 

<t>The value comprises a single field, the Path Protection Association Flags (32 bits), where each bit represents a
flag option. </t>

<t> The format of the <xref target="PPAG-TLV-Fmt"> Path Protection Association TLV</xref> is as follows:</t>

<figure anchor="PPAG-TLV-Fmt" title="Path Protection Association TLV format">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |         Type = TBD2         |              Length             |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |          Path Protection Association Flags                |S|P|
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

    <t>P (PROTECTION-LSP 1 bit) - Indicates whether the LSP associated with the PPAG is working or 
    protection LSP. If this flag is set, the LSP is a protection LSP.</t>
    <t>S (STANDBY 1 bit)-  When the  P flag is set, the S flag indicates whether the protection LSP associated
    with the PPAG is in standby mode. The S flag is ignored if the P flag is not set.</t>
    <t>Unassigned bits are considered reserved.  They MUST be set to 0 on
   transmission and MUST be ignored on receipt. </t>
<t>If the TLV is missing, it is considered that the LSP is the working LSP (i.e. P bit is unset).</t>
</section> <!-- PPAG TLV -->
</section> <!-- PCEP extensions --> 

<section anchor="Operation" title="Operation">
    <t>LSPs are associated with
   other LSPs with which they interact by adding them to a common
   association group via ASSOCIATION object. All procedures and error-handling for the ASSOCIATION 
   object is as per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.</t>

<section anchor="Operation-State-Sync" title="State Synchronization"> 

  <t>During state synchronization, a PCC MUST report all the existing path protection association groups 
  as well as any path protection flags to PCE(s) as per <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref>.</t>

    </section> <!-- State Synchronization --> 


    <section anchor="Operation-PCC-Init" title="PCC Initiated LSPs"> 

  <t>A PCC can associate a set of LSPs under its control for path protection purpose. Similarly, the PCC can 
  remove on or more LSPs under its control from the corresponding PPAG. In both cases, the PCC must report 
  the change in association to PCE(s) via PCRpt message. A PCC can also delegate the working and protection 
  LSPs to a stateful PCE, where PCE would control the LSPs. The stateful PCE could update the paths and attributes of the LSPs in the association group 
  via PCUpd message. A PCE could also update the association to PCC via PCUpd message. These procedures are described in <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref>.
</t>

</section> <!-- PCC Initiated LSPs --> 

    <section anchor="Operation-PCE-Init" title="PCE Initiated LSPs"> 

    <t>A PCE can create/update working and protection LSPs independently. 
    As specified in <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref>, 
    Association Groups can be created by both PCE and PCC. 
    Further, a PCE can remove a protection LSP from a PPAG as specified in 
    <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref>. The PCE uses PCUpd 
    or PCInitiate message to communicate the association information to the PCC.</t>

    </section> <!-- PCE Initiated LSPs --> 




    <section anchor="Session-Termination" title="Session Termination"> 

  <t>As per <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref> the association information is cleared along with the LSP state
   information.  When a PCEP
   session is terminated, after expiry of State Timeout Interval at PCC,
   the LSP state associated with that PCEP session is reverted to
   operator-defined default parameters or behaviors as per <xref target='RFC8231'></xref>.  Same procedure is
   also followed for the association information.  On session
   termination at the PCE, when the LSP state reported by PCC is
   cleared, the association information is also cleared as per <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref>.  Where there
   are no LSPs in a association group, the association is considered to
   be deleted..</t>

    </section> <!-- State Synchronization --> 

<section anchor="Operation-Error-Handling" title="Error Handling"> 

  <t>All LSPs (working or protection) within a PPAG MUST belong to the same TE Tunnel (as described in <xref target="RFC3209"/>) and have the same source and destination. 
  If a PCEP speaker attempts to add an LSP to a PPAG and the Tunnel ID (as carried in LSP-IDENTIFIERS TLV <xref target="RFC8231"/>, with description as per <xref target="RFC3209"/>) or source or destination of the LSP is different from 
  the LSP(s) in the PPAG, the PCC MUST send PCErr with Error-Type= 29 (Early allocation by IANA) (Association Error) <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref>
  and Error-Value = TBD3 (Tunnel ID or End points mismatch for Path Protection Association).</t>
  <t> There MUST be only one working LSP within a PPAG. If a PCEP Speaker attempts to add another working LSP,
  the PCEP peer MUST send PCErr with Error-Type=29 (Early allocation by IANA) (Association Error) <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref> 
  and Error-Value = TBD4
  (Attempt to add another working LSP for Path Protection Association).</t>
    </section> <!-- Error Handling --> 


</section> <!-- Operation --> 
<section title="Other considerations">
    <t>The working and protection LSPs are
   typically resource disjoint (e.g., node, srlg disjoint).  This
   ensures that a single failure will not affect both the working and
   protection LSPs.The disjoint requirement for a group of LSPs is handled via another association type called
        "Disjointness Association", as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-diversity"/>. 
        The diversity requirements for the the protection LSP are also handled by including both ASSOCIATION
        object identifying both the protection association group and disjoint association group for the group of LSPs.</t>
</section>    
<section title="IANA considerations">

    <section title="Association Type">

    <t>This document defines a new association type, originally
    defined in <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'/>, for path protection. 
    IANA is requested to make the assignment of a new value for the
    sub-registry "ASSOCIATION Type Field" (request to be created in <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'/>), as follows: </t>
            <texttable>
            <ttcol>Association Type Value</ttcol><ttcol>Association Name    </ttcol><ttcol>Reference</ttcol>
            <c> TBD1 </c><c> Path Protection Association</c> <c> This     document </c>
            </texttable>
    
    </section>
    
    <section title="PPAG TLV">

      <t> This document defines a new TLV for carrying additional information of LSPs within a path protection association group.
      IANA is requested to make the assignment of a new value for the
   existing "PCEP TLV Type Indicators" registry as follows:</t>

        <texttable>
        <ttcol>TLV Type Value</ttcol><ttcol>TLV Name</ttcol><ttcol> Reference</ttcol>
        <c> TBD2 </c><c>Path Protection Association Group TLV</c> <c> This document </c>
        </texttable>

<t> This document requests that a new sub-registry, named "Path protection Association Group TLV Flag Field", 
is created within the "Path Computation
   Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers" registry to manage the Flag field in
   the Path Protection Association Group TLV.
   New values are to be assigned by Standards Action <xref target="RFC8126"/>.  Each
   bit should be tracked with the following qualities:
</t> 
<t> Each bit should be tracked with the following qualities:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
    <t>Bit number (count from 0 as the most significant bit) </t>
    <t>Name flag </t> 
    <t>Reference </t> 
</list>
</t>
   
<texttable anchor="PPAG-TLV-Table-IANA" title="PPAG TLV">
    <ttcol align="center">Bit Number</ttcol>
    <ttcol align="center">Name</ttcol>
    <ttcol align="center">Reference</ttcol>
    <c>31</c>
    <c>P - PROTECTION-LSP</c>
    <c> This document </c>
    <c>30</c>
    <c>S - STANDBY</c>
    <c>This document</c>
</texttable>

    </section>

      <section title="PCEP Errors">

    <t>This document defines new Error-Type and Error-Value related to  path protection association. 
        IANA is requested to allocate new error values within the "PCEP-ERROR
   Object Error Types and Values" sub-registry of the PCEP Numbers
   registry, as follows:</t>
          <texttable>
           <ttcol> Error-Type </ttcol><ttcol> Meaning </ttcol><ttcol> Reference </ttcol>
           <c> 29 </c> <c> Association error</c> <c><xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref></c>
           <c></c><c> Error-value=TBD3: Tunnel ID or End points mismatch for Path Protection Association</c> <c> This document</c>
           <c></c><c> Error-value=TBD4: Attempt to add another working LSP for Path Protection Association</c> <c> This document</c>
          </texttable>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
        <t>
               The security considerations described in <xref target="RFC8231"/>, 
               <xref target="RFC8281"/>, and <xref target="RFC5440"/> 
               apply to the extensions described in this document as
   well.  Additional considerations related to associations where 
   a malicious PCEP speaker could be spoofed and could be used as
   an attack vector by creating associations is described in <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'></xref>. 
   Thus securing the PCEP session using
   Transport Layer Security (TLS) <xref target="RFC8253"/>, as per the
   recommendations and best current practices in <xref target="RFC7525"/>, is
   RECOMMENDED.
        </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Manageability Considerations" toc="default">
      <section title="Control of Function and Policy" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any control or policy 
            requirements in addition to those already listed in
        <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and 
        <xref target="RFC8281"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Information and Data Models" toc="default">
        <t><xref target="RFC7420"/> describes the PCEP MIB, there are no new MIB Objects
        for this document.</t>
        <t>The PCEP YANG module <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang"/> supports
        associations.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Liveness Detection and Monitoring" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new liveness detection
        and monitoring requirements in addition to those already listed in
        <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and 
        <xref target="RFC8281"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Verify Correct Operations" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new operation
        verification requirements in addition to those already listed in
        <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and 
        <xref target="RFC8281"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Requirements On Other Protocols" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new requirements
        on other protocols.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Impact On Network Operations" toc="default">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not have any impact on
        network operations in addition to those already listed in
        <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and 
        <xref target="RFC8281"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgments">
    <t>We would like to thank Jeff Tantsura and Xian Zhang for their contributions to this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
    
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3209"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5440"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8231"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8281"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"?>        
    </references>
    <references title="Information References">
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4427"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4655"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4657"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7420"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7525"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8051"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8253"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang"?>
        <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pce-association-diversity"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
