<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-li-pce-sr-bidir-path-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Bi-didirectional SR Path in PCEP">PCEP Extension for
    Segment Routing Bi-directional Path</title>

    <author fullname="Cheng Li" initials="C." surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>chengli13@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mach(Guoyi) Chen" initials="M." surname="Chen">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>Mach.chen@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dhruv Dhody" initials="D." surname="Dhody">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street> Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield </street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560066</code>

          <country>India </country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>dhruv.ietf@gmail.com </email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Zhenbin Li" initials="Z." surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>lizhenbin@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jie Dong" initials="J." surname="Dong">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>jie.dong@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="8" month="April" year="2018"/>

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>Interdomain Routing Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) provides
      mechanisms for Path Computation Elements (PCEs) to perform path
      computations in response to Path Computation Clients (PCCs) requests.
      The Stateful PCE extensions allow stateful control of Multiprotocol
      Label Switching (MPLS) Traffic Engineering (TE) Label Switched Paths
      (LSPs) using PCEP. Futhermore, PCEP can be used for computing
      uni-directional Segment Routing path. However, Bi-directional SR path is
      required to be supported in many scenarios like mobile backhaul
      transport network. The bi-directional SR path is defined in <xref
      target="I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment"/>.</t>

      <t>For supporting SR bi-directional path computation, this document
      specifies PCEP extensions for grouping two reverse unidirectional SR
      paths into an Associated Bidirectional SR path when using a Stateful PCE
      for both PCE-Initiated and PCC-Initiated LSPs as well as when using a
      Stateless PCE.</t>

      <t/>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Segment routing (SR) <xref target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing"/>
      leverages the source routing and tunneling paradigms. SR supports to
      steer packets into an explicit forwarding path according to the Segment
      Routing Policy ( SR Policy) <xref
      target="I-D.filsfils-spring-segment-routing-policy"/> at the ingress
      node.</t>

      <t>However, the SR Policies defined in <xref
      target="I-D.filsfils-spring-segment-routing-policy"/> only supports
      uni-directional SR paths. For supporting bi-directional paths <xref
      target="I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment"/>, new SR policies carrying
      Path ID and bi-directional path information are defined in <xref
      target="I-D.li-idr-sr-policy-path-segment-distribution"/>.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/> specifies extensions to
      the Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) <xref target="RFC5440"/>
      that allow a stateful PCE <xref target="RFC8231"/> to compute and
      initiate Traffic Engineering (TE) paths, as well as a PCC to request a
      path subject to certain constraint(s) and optimization criteria in SR
      networks. </t>

      <t>However, it does not support bi-directional SR path computation, so
      new extensions are required. </t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> introduces a generic
      mechanism to create a grouping of LSPs which can then be used to define
      associations between a set of LSPs and/or a set of attributes, for
      example primary and secondary LSP associations, and is equally
      applicable to the active and passive modes of a Stateful PCE <xref
      target="RFC8231"/> or a stateless PCE <xref target="RFC5440"/>.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> defines PCEP
      extensions for grouping two reverse unidirectional MPLS TE LSPs into an
      Associated Bidirectional LSP when using a Stateful PCE for both
      PCE-Initiated and PCC-Initiated LSPs as well as when using a Stateless
      PCE.</t>

      <t/>

      <t>This document specifies PCEP extensions for grouping two reverse
      unidirectional SR paths into a bi-directional SR path when using a
      Stateful PCE for both PCE-Initiated and PCC-Initiated paths as well as
      when using a Stateless PCE. For binding SR paths, the PATH-ID TLV
      [draft-li-pce-path-segment] MUST be included in the LSP object. The path
      ID can be a path segment in SR-MPLS <xref
      target="I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment"/>, or a path ID in SRv6
      <xref target="I-D.li-spring-passive-pm-for-srv6-np"/>, or other IDs that
      can identify an SR path.</t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This memo makes use of the terms defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/>. The reader is assumed to be
      familiar with the terminology defined in <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref
      target="RFC8231"/>, <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> and
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="PCEP Extension for Bi-directional Path">
      <t>This document describes the mechanism of carring bi-directional path
      information in PCEP messages. For binding two SR paths into a single
      bi-directional path, PATH-ID TLVs should be included in LSP objects as
      described in [draft-li-pce-path-segment]. Futhermore, this document
      defines an association group objects, Double-sided Bi-directional SR
      Path Association Group object for associating SR paths.</t>

      <section title="Double-sided Bi-directional SR Path Association Group Object">
        <t>As defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>, two
        LSPs are associated as a bi-directional LSP by a common bi-directional
        LSP association group. For associating two SR paths, this document
        defines a Double-sided Bi-directional SR Path Association Groups. The
        Association Type of Double-sided Bidirectional SRv6 Path Association
        Group is TBD.</t>

        <t/>

        <t>A member of the Double-sided Bi-directional SR Path Association
        Group can take the role of a forward or reverse SR path and follows
        the rules similar to the rules defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> for LSPs.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>An SR path (forward or reverse) can not be part of more than
            one Double-sided Bi-directional SR Path Association Group. More
            than one forward SR and/ or reverse SR path can be part of a
            Double-sided Bi-directional SR Association Group. </t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The SR paths belonging to this association are conveyed via PCEP
        messages to the PCEP peer. The object endcoding follows the rules
        defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.</t>

        <t>The Association ID, Association Source, optional Global Association
        Source and optional Extended Association ID in the Bi-directional SR
        Path Association Group Object are initialized using the procedures
        defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> and <xref
        target="RFC7551"/>. </t>

        <t>For describing the SR paths in a association group, such as
        direction and co-routed information, this document reuses the
        Bi-directional LSP Association Group TLV defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>. All fields and processing
        rules are defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>.
        </t>

        <t> </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Procedures of Bi-directional Path Computation">
      <t>As defined in <xref target="RFC5440"/>, the B-flag in RP object MUST
      be set when the PCC specifies that the path computation request relates
      to a bi-directional TE LSP. In this document, the B-flag also MUST be
      set when the PCC specifies that the path computation request relates to
      a bi-directional SR path. Likely, when a stateful PCE initiates or
      updates a bi-directional paths including LSPs and SR paths, the B-flag
      in SRP object <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-stateful-pce-gmpls"/> MUST
      be set as well.</t>

      <t>The bi-directional path computation can be divided into two
      uni-directional path computations. Thus the operations of path
      computation and path ID allocation for uni-directional path as defined
      in [draft-li-pce-sr-path-segment] can apply to bi-directional path
      computation directly.</t>

      <t>Two uni-directional paths can be associated by the association group
      object <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> with the same
      association ID and the same association type. A bi-directional path
      association group object has been defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> for binding paths in MPLS. As
      defined in this document, two SR paths with the PATH-ID TLV
      [draft-li-pce-sr-path-segment] included in the LSP object can be
      associated by a Bi-directional SR Path Association Group with the same
      association ID.</t>

      <t/>

      <t>After path computation, the bi-directional path that combined by two
      SR paths and associated by an association group object will be sent to
      the source and destination PCC( as known as the ingress node and egress
      node in SR) by PCRep or PCUdp or PCInitiate messages, respectively. </t>

      <t>A PCEP message such as PCRep or PCUdp or PCInitiate, containing a
      bi-directional path, sent to the PCC contains a forward direction path
      beginning from itself to the remote PCC and a reverse path from the
      remote PCC back to the PCC itself. The information of reverse direction
      path can be used for several scenarios, such as directed BFD <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-mpls-bfd-directed"/>.</t>

      <t/>

      <section title="PCE Initiated SR Paths">
        <t>Being identical to the rules specified in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> and <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>, Double-sided Bi-directional
        SR Path Association Groups can be created by a Stateful PCE. </t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Stateful PCE can create and update the forward and reverse SR
            path independently for Double-sided Bi-directional SR Path
            Association Groups.</t>

            <t>Stateful PCE can establish and remove the association
            relationship on a per SR path basis.</t>

            <t>Stateful PCE can create and update the SR path and the
            association on a PCC via PCInitiate and PCUpd messages,
            respectively, using the procedures described in <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.</t>
          </list><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                                     +-----+
                                     | PCE |
                                     +-----+
         PCUpd/PCInitiate            /    \         PCUpd/PCInitiate
         Tunnel 1 (F)               /      \        Tunnel 2 (R)
         (LSP1 (F), LSP2 (R))      /        \       (LSP2 (F), LSP1 (R))
                                  /          \
                                 /            \
                                v              v
                           +-----+    LSP1     +-----+
                           |  S  |------------>|  D  |
                           |     |<------------|     |
                           +-----+    LSP2     +-----+

          Figure 1: PCE-Initiated Double-sided Bidirectional SR Path


]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="PCC Initiated SR Paths">
        <t>Being identical to the rules specified in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> and <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>, Double-sided Bi-directional
        SR Path Association Groups can also be created by a PCC.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>PCC can create and update the forward and reverse SR paths
            independently for Double-sided Bi-directional SR Path Association
            Groups.</t>

            <t>PCC can establish and remove the association relationship on a
            per SR path basis.</t>

            <t>PCC MUST report the change in the association group of an SR
            path to PCE(s) via PCRpt message.</t>

            <t>PCC can report the forward and reverse SR paths independently
            to PCE(s) via PCRpt message.</t>

            <t>PCC can delegate the forward and reverse SR paths independently
            to a Stateful PCE, where PCE would control the SR paths.</t>

            <t>Stateful PCE can update the SR paths in the Double-sided
            Bi-directional SR Path Association Group via PCUpd message, using
            the procedures described in <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.</t>
          </list><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                                     +-----+
                                     | PCE |
                                     +-----+
         Reports/Delegates:          ^    ^       Reports/Delegates
         Tunnel 1 (F)               /      \        Tunnel 2 (R)
         (LSP1 (F), LSP2 (R))      /        \       (LSP2 (F), LSP1 (R))
                                  /          \
                                 /            \
                                /              \
                            +-----+    LSP1     +-----+
                            |  S  |------------>|  D  |
                            |     |<------------|     |
                            +-----+    LSP2     +-----+

           Figure 2: PCC-Initiated Double-sided Bidirectional SR Path

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Stateless PCE">
        <t>As defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>, for
        a stateless PCE, it might be useful to associate a path computation
        request to an association group, thus enabling it to associate a
        common set of configuration parameters or behaviors with the request.
        A PCC can request co-routed or non co-routed forward and reverse
        direction paths from a stateless PCE for a bidirectional LSP
        association group. </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>TBA</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBA</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t/>

      <t/>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.filsfils-spring-segment-routing-policy'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.li-spring-passive-pm-for-srv6-np'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8231'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5440'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-mpls-bfd-directed'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8281"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.li-idr-sr-policy-path-segment-distribution'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-stateful-pce-gmpls'

?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3209'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7551'?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
