<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-xxx-pce-controlled-id-space-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PCE Controlled ID Space">PCE Controlled ID Space</title>

    <author fullname="Cheng Li" initials="C." surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>chengli13@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mach(Guoyi) Chen" initials="M." surname="Chen">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>Mach.chen@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jie Dong" initials="J." surname="Dong">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>jie.dong@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Zhenbin Li" initials="Z." surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>lizhenbin@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="11" month="May" year="2018"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>In some use cases, such as binding SID and SR path SID allocation, a
      stateful PCE may need to dynamically allocate new labels or Segment IDs
      that come from a PCC's label space. However, in the existing documents,
      the label range to be used by a PCE is assumed to to be known and set on
      both PCEP peers, so the mechanism of label range delegation is required.
      This document describes a mechanism to advertise specific PCE controlled
      ID spaces to PCEs via PCEP channel. The type of ID can be MPLS label,
      SRv6 path ID or other ID.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="RFC5440"/> defines the stateless Path Computation
      Element communication Protocol (PCEP) for Path Computation Elements
      (PCEs) to perform path computations in response to Path Computation
      Clients (PCCs) requests. For supporting stateful operations, <xref
      target="RFC8231"/> specifies a set of extensions to PCEP to enable
      stateful control of LSPs within and across PCEP sessions in compliance
      with <xref target="RFC4657"/>. Futhermore, <xref target="RFC8281"/>
      describes the setup, maintenance, and teardown of PCE-initiated LSPs
      under the stateful PCE model, without the need for local configuration
      on the PCC, thus allowing for a dynamic network that is centrally
      controlled and deployed. </t>

      <t/>

      <t><xref target="RFC8283"/> introduces the architecture for PCE as a
      central controller, examines the motivations and applicability for PCEP
      as a control protocol in this environment, and introduces the
      implications for the protocol. Also, <xref
      target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller"/> specifies the
      procedures and PCEP protocol extensions for using the PCE as the central
      controller, where LSPs are calculated/setup/initiated and label
      forwarding entries are downloaded through extending PCEP.</t>

      <t>However, these documents do not describe the mechanisms for PCEs to
      manage the space of MPLS label and allocate MPLS label for each of the
      routers that it controls. The label range to be used by a PCE is assumed
      to be known and set on both PCEP peers <xref
      target="I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller"/>.</t>

      <t>For solving this problem, this document describes a mechanism to
      advertise the range of MPLS label, SRv6 path ID <xref
      target="I-D.li-spring-passive-pm-for-srv6-np"/> via PCEP extensions. The
      ID space range information can be advertised via the TLVs in the Open
      message. The detailed procedures will be described in section 4, and the
      objects' format will be introduced in section 5.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This memo makes use of the terms defined in <xref target="RFC5440"/>
      and <xref target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Use cases">
      <t/>

      <section title="Binding SID Allocation">
        <t>As defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing"/>, the
        binding SID is bound to an SR policy, instantiation of which may
        involve a list of SIDs. In several scenarios, SR policies need to be
        dynamically updated according to the network status and operation
        policies. Therefore, a PCE needs to obtain the authority to allocate
        labels actively from the PCC's specific label space.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Path ID Allocation">
        <t>For indicating an SR path, an SR Path Segment and SRv6 path ID are
        defined in <xref target="I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment"/> and
        <xref target="I-D.li-spring-passive-pm-for-srv6-np"/>
        respectively.</t>

        <t>An SR path ID will be allocated dynamically triggered by a SR path
        computation. A PCE needs to obtain the authority so that it can
        allocate path IDs actively from the PCC's specific path ID space.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview of ID delegation">
      <t>When a PCEP session is establishing, Open messages will be sent
      between PCCs and PCEs. Capabilities can be conveied by the Capabiliies
      TLVs in the Open message. For delegating ID space to a stateful PCE, a
      PCC MUST include ID Space TLVs in Open messages to inform the PCE the
      range of ID space. This document defines LABEL-SPACE-DELEGATION and
      SRv6-PATH-ID-SPACE-DELEGATION TLVs.</t>

      <t>For delegating multiple types of ID space, multiple ID space TLVs
      will be included in a Open message. Each type of ID space TLV will be
      included only once in a Open Message. The ID type can be MPLS label,
      SRv6 path ID <xref target="I-D.li-spring-passive-pm-for-srv6-np"/> or
      other ID.</t>

      <t>The procedure of ID space delegation is shown below:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
             +-+-+                                   +-+-+
             |PCC|                                   |PCE|
             +-+-+                                   +-+-+
               |                                       |
               |                                       |
1) Open        | ---------------- Open --------------> |
 PCC->PCE      |   LABEL-SPACE/SRv6-PATH-ID-SPACE TLV  |
               |                                       |
               | <------------- KeepAlive -----------  |
               |                                       |
               |                                       |

                 Figure 5: ID Delegation Procedures
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>If the delegation is successful, the PCE will return a KeepAlive
      message to the PCC. If there is any error in processing ID delegation,
      an Error (PCErr) message will be sent to the PCC.</t>

      <t>If the PCE can not process ID space delegation TLVs, then the PCE
      should send a PCErr message with Error-type=1 (PCEP session
      establishment failure) and and Error-value=1 (reception of an invalid
      Open message or a non Open message).</t>

      <t>After ID delegation, a stateful PCE can learn the PCE controlled ID
      spaces delegated from PCCs and then it can allocate IDs within the
      delegated ID space actively. For example, a PCE can actively allocate
      global or local labels/IDs such as binding segments <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing"/> and path ID <xref
      target="I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment"/> <xref
      target="I-D.li-spring-passive-pm-for-srv6-np"/> according to the
      delegated ID space and the SRGB and SRLB information of a PCC. SRGB and
      SRLB information of a PCC can be learned from IGP synchronization or
      other ways. This is out of scope of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Objects">
      <t/>

      <section title="Open Object">
        <t>For advertising the PCE controlled ID space to a PCE, this document
        defines several TLVs within the Open object.</t>

        <section title="LABEL-SPACE-DELEGATION TLV">
          <t>For advertising PCE controlled label spaces to a PCE, this
          document defines a LABEL-SPACE-DELEGATION TLV.</t>

          <t>The LABEL-SPACE-DELEGATION TLV is an optional TLV for use in the
          OPEN object, and its format is shown in the following figure:</t>

          <t><figure>
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
       0                   1                   2                   3
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |            Type=TBA           |            Length             |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                             Flags                           |A|
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                            Start 1                            |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                            Range 1                            |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                              ...                              |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                              ...                              |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                            Start n                            |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                            Range n                            |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

                     Figure 2. LABEL-SPACE-DELEGATION TLV
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The type (16 bits) of the TLV is TBA. The length field is a 16
          bits variable.</t>

          <t>Flags (24 bits):</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>A-flag: All space flag, set when all the label space is
              delegated to a PCE. When A-flag is set, the pair of Start and
              End SHOULD NOT appear unless the PCC needs to notify the entire
              ID space to a PCE.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The rest bits of Flags field MUST be set to 0 on transmission and
          MUST be ignored on receipt.</t>

          <t>Start n: indicates the beginning of the label block n.</t>

          <t>Range n: indicates the range of the label block n.</t>

          <t>The numbuer of label blocks can be calculated according to value
          of the length filed.</t>

          <t>A stateful PCE can actively allocate labels to an LSP or an SR
          Policy. For example, binding SIDs <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing"/> can be seleted from the
          delegated label space and then allocated by a stateful PCE actively.
          Also, Path segment <xref
          target="I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment"/> can be allocated by a
          stateful PCE in the same way.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="SRv6-PATH-ID-SPACE-DELEGATION TLV">
          <t>For advertising the delegated SRv6 Path ID <xref
          target="I-D.li-spring-passive-pm-for-srv6-np"/> space to a PCE, this
          document defines an SRv6-PATH-ID-SPACE-DELEGATION TLV.</t>

          <t>The SRv6-PATH-ID-SPACE-DELEGATION TLV is an optional TLV for use
          in the OPEN object, and its format is shown in the following
          figure:</t>

          <t><figure>
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
       0                   1                   2                   3
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |            Type=TBA           |            Length             |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                             Flags                           |A|
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                            Start 1                            |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                            Range 1                            |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                              ...                              |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                              ...                              |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                            Start n                            |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                            Range n                            |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

                    Figure 2. SRv6-PATH-ID-SPACE-DELEGATION TLV

]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The type (16 bits) of the TLV is TBA. The length field is a 16
          bits variable.</t>

          <t>Flags (24 bits):</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>A-flag: All Space flag, set when all the ID space is
              delegated to a PCE. When A-flag is set, the pair of Start and
              End SHOULD NOT appear unless PCC needs to notify the entire ID
              space to a PCE.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The rest bits of Flags field MUST be set to 0 on transmission and
          MUST be ignored on receipt.</t>

          <t>Start n: indicates the beginning of the SRv6 Path ID block n.</t>

          <t>Range n: indicates the range of the SRv6 Path ID block n.</t>

          <t>The numbuer of ID blocks can be calculated according to the
          length filed. Given the controlled ID spaces, a stateful PCE can
          actively allocate path IDs to SR paths by selecting from the
          controlled ID spaces. </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>TBA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TBA.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.cheng-spring-mpls-path-segment'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.li-spring-passive-pm-for-srv6-np'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8231'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5440'?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8281"?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4657'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.zhao-pce-pcep-extension-for-pce-controller'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8283'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
